בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף Daf is פ"ב Peh Bais 82.
We pick up in the bottom of פ"א עמוד ב' Peh Amud
Beis and we're in the middle of the עשר תקנות eser takanos
that יהושע Yehoshua made with בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael when they entered
into the land, basically something that demanded a certain compromise of personal
property rights for the sake of the benefit of the larger community.
And the last one is about ten lines before the lines get
wider: ומת מצוה. U-mes mitzva. Okay, מת מצוה קונה מקומו, Mes mitzva
koneh mekomo, wherever you find a dead body you can bury it
in that
place if there's no obvious family that it belongs to. So the
גמרא Gemara says ורמינהו, V'reminhu, I'll ask you on this: המוצא מת
מוטל באסטרטיה, Hamotzei mes mutal ba'esratya, if you find a dead body
lying in the middle of like a אסטרטיה, esratya, אסטרטיה esratya is
a Greek word and it means like a major road. מפנה לימין
אסטרטיה או לשמאל אסטרטיה, Mafne liyamin esratya o lismoal esratya, you don't
bury him right in the middle of the road itself, you move
him to the right or to the left, you bury him in
some field nearby. שדה בור ושדה ניר, Sadeh bor v'sadeh nir, you
have to choose between a vacant lot and a plowed lot, a
ניר nir is like plowed but nothing is growing there, but you
know be turned over the dirt. מפנה לשדה בור, Mafne l'sadeh bor,
you bring it to a vacant lot, an unplowed lot, right? Because
better to create the least amount of damage possible. שדה בור ושדה
ניר ושדה זרע, Sadeh bor v'sadeh nir v'sadeh zera, if it's between
a plowed but unplanted lot and a planted field, מפנה לשדה ניר,
Mafne l'sadeh nir, you do it to the plowed field, plowed like
you know the dirt is turned over. היו שתיהן בורות שתיהן נירות
שתיהן זרועות, Hayu shteihen boros shteihen nirot shteihen zruot, if they were
both if both the right and the left were the same choice,
they were both types of both the same types of fields, מפנה
למקום שירצה, Mafne l'makom sheyirtze, whichever one you choose. There's no rule.
Hopefully you'll make some choice which is guided by some logical principle.
אמר רב ביבי, Amar Rav Bibi, so anyway how do you deal
with this? Here it says you don't bury him straight in the
middle of where you found him. But of course the obvious answer
is that here we're not talking about talking about a special case
that he's right there in the middle of a major thoroughfare and
the problem is is that even if you could you know halt
traffic for a while to bury him, everybody who's going to go
over that thoroughfare is going to become טמא, tamai, is going to
become impure, right? So that's the obvious answer. אמר רב ביבי במוטל
על המיצר, Amar Rav Bibi b'mutal al hametzar, he is the way
רש"י Rashi explains it is that he's lying across the from one
edge to the next of the road, from boundary to boundary. ומתוך
שניתן לפנותו, U-metoch shenitan l'fnoto, and once you have to move him
anyway because you're obviously there's no way you're going to bury him
in the middle of the road, מפנה לכל מקום שירצה, Mafne l'chol
makom sheyirtze, then you make some type of a choice and if
they're equal choices then you do the one that makes the most
sense. Okay, so that's the list of the ten. Now the גמרא
Gemara says אמרי, Amri, look, if you take a look at it
the גמרא Gemara says עשרה, Asara, how can you say there are
ten? הני חד עשר הויין, Hanei chad asar havyen, these are there
are eleven. עשרה הני, Asara hanei, so so if you counted them,
I wasn't counting, but if you counted them there's eleven, not ten.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, מהלכין בשבילי הרשות, Mahlchim b'shvilei ha-reshus,
cutting through somebody's like field when it's not being planted, you know
at a time when it doesn't matter because nothing is growing there.
So that שלמה אמרה, Shlomo amra, that's really not one of the
תקנות takanot of יהושע, Yehoshua, that's really based on a principle we
learn from שלמה, Shlomo, so it doesn't really count as one of
the as one of as one. So without that there are ten.
כדתניא, Ke'detanya, like we taught in a ברייתא. Braysa. הרי שכלו פירותיו
מן השדה, Harei shekalu peirotav min hasadeh, somebody's fruit is no longer
growing in the field, it's all been harvested and the new stuff
has not yet started growing, ואינו מניח בני אדם ליכנס בתוך
שדהו, V'eino maniach bnei adam l'hikanes b'soch sado, and he doesn't care,
he's standing on his property right and he doesn't let people cut
through his field. So מה הבריות אומרות עליו, Mah habriyot omrot alav,
what will people say about him? מה הנאה לפלוני, Mah hana'ah l'ploni,
what benefit does that guy have keeping people out of his field?
ומה הבריות מזיקות לו, U-mah habriyot mazikos lo, how are people hurting
him? Why you know what a stingy whatever just you know person,
what does it do for him that he's not letting us cross
his field? Okay, so it's basically like a classic definition of you
know זה נהנה וזה אינו חסר, Zeh ne'ene v'zeh eino chaser, we
could benefit, it's not hurting you, what are you doing like not
letting people go through? So technically you're not doing anything illegal but
it's obviously you know improper and immoral. So the גמרא Gemara says
עליו הכתוב אומר, Alav hakatuv omer, regarding him the verse says מהיות
טוב אל תקרי רע, Miheyos tov al tikre ra, from being you
know
if you have a choice to be good why should you be
bad? Don't be called evil. So the גמרא Gemara says ומי כתיב
מהיות טוב אל תקרי רע, U-mi ksiv miheyos tov al tikre ra,
what do you mean as the verse says? It doesn't there's no
verse that says this. Now I didn't check Steinsaltz but I am
willing to bet you dollars to donuts that this is a this
is a פסוק pasuk from בן סירא. Ben Sira. The גמרא Gemara
a number of times quotes בן סירא Ben Sira which is one
of the Apocrypha and says as it is written, even though you're
not supposed to actually even be learning the Apocrypha, the גמרא Gemara
knew בן סירא Ben Sira pretty well. So anyway that's my guess,
but the גמרא Gemara says no that's not a פסוק. pasuk. So
the גמרא Gemara says אִין כְּתִיב כְּהַאי גַוְונָא, In ksiv ki hai
gavna, it's based on a פסוק pasuk because there's a פסוק pasuk
that says כי האי גוונא ki hai gavna just like this: אל
תמנע טוב מבעליו בהיות לאל ידך, Al timna tov mibalaiv biheyos le'el
yadecha, do not hold back good from its owners, like do not
you know not do good to somebody you know when you're able
to. Or maybe it means don't actually show gratitude. בהיות לאל ידך
Biheyos le'el yadecha when there's you have the ability in
you.
in משלי. Mishlei.
So גמרא Gemara says וותו ליכא, v'tu leka, what, there’s no more
than these ten eleven? והאיכא, v'hai ka, here’s some others that רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda teaches. תני רבי יהודה אומר, Tani Rabbi Yehuda omer,
בשעת הוצאת זבלים be-sha'at hotza'at z'valim when you’re taking out, when it’s
the time to sort of take out the dung, מוציא אדם זבלו
לרשות הרבים, motzi adam zivlo l'reshut harabim, you have a right to
bring it out to the public domain, וצובר כל שלשים יום v'tzover
kol shloshim yom and you should pile it up there for thirty
days, כדי שיישוף רגלי אדם ורגלי בהמה k'dei she-yishof raglei adam v'raglei
behema so that it should be sort of like stepped on by
people and I don’t know, somehow that improves the dung, I don’t
exactly get it, maybe it’s not dung, maybe it means like refuse,
and as people are walking on it anyway it turns it into
more usable fertilizer, okay, שעל מנת כן הנחיל יהושע את הארץ, she-al
m'nat ken hinchil Yehoshua et ha-aretz, that was the stipulation when they
entered into the land, that people would have a right to do
that, to bring this stuff and to put it in the public
domain because that’s something that everybody has a use for. So the
גמרא Gemara says והאיכא, v'hai ka, and there’s another one that’s a
condition of יהושע. Yehoshua. דתני רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי
יוחנן בן ברוקא, D'tani Rabbi Yishmael beno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka,
what רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael teaches, תני רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי
יוחנן בן ברוקא אומר, tani Rabbi Yishmael beno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben
Beroka omer, he says תנאי בית דין הוא, tnai bet din hu,
it’s a condition of the court,
שזה יורד לתוך שדה חברו she-ze yored l'toch sdeh chavero וקוצץ שכו
של חברו v'kotzetz shacho shel chavero להציל נחילו שלו. lehatzil n'chilo she-lo.
Let’s say my bees have swarmed onto you into your property and
they’ve all hovering around a branch. So the only way I can
effectively bring that swarm of bees back to my yard is by
cutting off that branch and bringing it with me and then they’ll
follow, they’ll stay around the branch. So I have a right to
do that. You can’t say, oh no, it’s my branch, you can’t
do it. I have a right to do it. Maybe I’ll pay
you for the branch, but I have a right to do it.
ונותן לו דמי שכו של חברו v'noten lo d'mei shacho shel chavero
and you pay him for the branch of your friend, ותנאי בית
דין הוא, v'tnai bet din hu, it’s a condition of the court,
שזה שופך יינו she-ze shofech yeino מציל דבשו של חברו matzil dvasho
shel chavero ונוטל דמי יינו מתוך דבשו. v'notel d'mei yeino mi-toch dvasho.
I can spill my wine in order to save your honey if
I see your barrel of honey is breaking, and but you’ll have
to pay me back for my wine. Okay? You can’t say, I
didn’t ask you to spill your wine. Okay? ותנאי בית דין הוא,
v'tnai bet din hu, and it’s a condition of the court, שזה
מפרק עציו וטוען פשתנו של חברו. she-ze m'farek eitzav v'toen pishtano shel
chavero. Let’s say I’m going with my donkey and I’m carrying firewood
and I see that you, your donkey
has broken its leg and you have this flax which is very
expensive and it’s all going to get damaged. I can take out
my firewood off my donkey, load my donkey up with your flax,
and you’ll have to pay me back for my firewood, okay? וטוען
פשתנו של חברו ונוטל דמי עציו מתוך פשתנו של חברו v'toen pishtano
shel chavero v'notel d'mei eitzav mi-toch pishtano shel chavero and I can
make you pay for it. Now for us we would see like,
why do you need תנאי בית דין? tnai bet din? That’s a
logical thing, you know? I mean, it’s expensive. But we didn’t make
explicit תנאי tnai and stipulation, I just did it and therefore you
have to pay me back for my expenses. תוספות Tosafot by the
way is bothered with this because if you remember there’s another גמרא
Gemara that says that when I spill my wine to save your
honey you only have to pay me my fee, you don’t have
to actually pay for the loss of the wine. So תוספות Tosafot
basically says that in this case you, the guy whose honey is
being lost, actually are the one that you jump up and you
spill out my wine or you force me to spill out my
wine, in that case you have to pay me for my wine.
All right, anyway, שעל מנת כן הנחיל יהושע לישראל את הארץ. she-al
m'nat ken hinchil Yehoshua l’Yisrael et ha-aretz. That was a condition. So
the גמרא Gemara says ah, you see that there are others than
just the ones we listed? So the גמרא Gemara says ביחידאי לא
קאמינא. be-yachidai lo ka-amina. We’re not dealing with things that are taught
in the name of individual opinions, we’re dealing with something that is
taught unanimously. Does that mean that other people disagree with this or
does it just mean that it’s not being taught unanimously? That’s not
so clear. Okay, so top of eighty-one A. והא כי אתא רבין
אמר רבי יוחנן, v'ha ki ata Ravin amar Rabbi Yochanan, when רבין
Ravin came he said in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
אחד אילן הנוטה לתוך שדה חברו echad ilan ha-notteh l'toch sdeh chavero
ואחד אילן הסמוך למצר v'echad ilan ha-samuch la-metzar מביא וקורא, meivi v'koreh,
שעל מנת כן הנחיל יהושע לישראל את הארץ. she-al m'nat ken hinchil
Yehoshua l'Yisrael et ha-aretz. So he teaches the following ברייתא, Baraita, it’s
not that he
says, he says in the name of
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, he says in the name of רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan that if you have a tree that is inclining over
somebody else’s field or it’s near a boundary line that you bring
ביכורים Bikkurim from the tree. Now the question is of course the
tree if the tree is in your yard why wouldn’t you bring
ביכורים Bikkurim from the tree? So the answer is because there’s another
opinion in the גמרא Gemara that says since you don’t have a
right to have your tree right there because you’re
shading or damaging my field, it’s hanging over my field, you should
have to cut it or whatever, so therefore your essentially your tree
even though it’s planted in your property is illegitimately planted because of
the impact it’s having on my property. So there’s a position in
the גמרא Gemara that you’re not allowed to bring ביכורים Bikkurim from
it because it shouldn't be there in the first place. And רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says no, יהושע Yehoshua said one of the conditions
of יהושע Yehoshua is you’re allowed to bring it. Okay, and therefore,
and רש"י Rashi I’m sorry, רש"י Rashi says that this is a
ברייתא Baraita and therefore if it’s a ברייתא Baraita and it’s a
ברייתא Baraita being taught unanimously, I mean it’s quoted by רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan but presumably it’s a unanimous ברייתא, Baraita, so why isn’t
this listed in the list of the ten that we taught earlier?
So the גמרא Gemara says אלא מאן תנא עשרה תנאים שהתנה יהושע
ספויי Ela man tana asarah tnaim she-hitna Yehoshua? S'fuyai the גמרא Gemara
says. So the original teaching of the ten... conditions of יהושע Yehoshua
is not a ברייתא. Braita. That actually is the opinion of an
אמורא. Amora. That’s יהושע בן לוי Yehoshua ben Levi בן לוי ben
Levi who that was just in the name of יהושע בן לוי.
Yehoshua ben Levi. So sure there are others that say that there
are more or there are different תנאים, tnaim, it’s not some unanimous
ברייתא, Braita, that’s a particular opinion that those were the ten conditions.
רב גביה מבי כסילי מתני לה דהדיא. Rav Geviah miBei Kasil matni
la dehedya. רב גביה Rav Geviah from בי כסילי Bei Kasil teaches
explicitly. רב תנחום ורב בירס אמרי. Rav Tanchum v’Rav Beris amri. רב
תנחום Rav Tanchum following quote. רב תנחום ורב בירס Rav Tanchum v’Rav
Beris say משום זקן אחד, mishum zakein echad, in the name of
an elder, ומאן הוא, u’manhu, and who is that elder? יהושע בן
לוי. Yehoshua ben Levi. And what does יהושע בן לוי Yehoshua ben
Levi say? עשרה תנאים התנה יהושע, Asara tnaim hisni Yehoshua, ten conditions.
So it is not an anonymous ברייתא, Braita, it’s possible there are
different opinions about that list, but that’s his list. Okay. Now the
גמרא Gemara moves on from the ten conditions of יהושע Yehoshua to
a ten conditions in the time of עזרא. Ezra. And עזרא Ezra
was like in the second coming back into the land. Now what’s
interesting in terms of the shift of emphasis here is that the
phrase by יהושע Yehoshua is הנחיל יהושע את הארץ. hinchil Yehoshua et
ha’aretz. He bequeathed them the land. And it was very much about
ownership of the land, setting up Jewish society in the land, right
in the sense of like communal needs and you know individual rights
and all of that. That was very much the theme there. עזרא,
Ezra, you know, he was more like the first rabbi, right? I
mean he was the one, you know, he was not the one
that they were settling in the land because they had the political
they were given the right from כורש, Koresh, you know, from the
from the Persian king there. It was not like עזרא Ezra was
the one who was determining their like political sense of you know
of their you know of the structure and their ownership. He was
the one that was like leading them religiously. So his תקנות takkanot
are going to be of a very different type of a nature,
much more of a religious nature.
Let’s take a look.
They did not have sovereignty under עזרא. Ezra. They did not have
sovereignty. The first time they got some degree of sovereignty was at
the time of the חשמונאים. Chashmonaim. Until then they were really under
the control of whatever foreign government had owned you know was in
control of the land of ישראל. Yisrael. יהושע Yehoshua did. Exactly. So
yeah it wasn’t right correct. The word sovereignty is a keyword, correct.
So that’s that is a key difference here. So they’re settling in
the time of עזרא, Ezra, you know, and the גמרא Gemara before
was presuming that the תקנות takkanos of יהושע Yehoshua lasted through their
day and age and even maybe in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or
in בבל, Bavel, but nevertheless the sense of what type of leadership
somebody is doing and you know the role someone is playing, by
יהושע Yehoshua it was like he was a king as it were
almost, you know political leader, it was about sovereignty, it was about
setting up the political economic structure, עזרא Ezra it’s much more religious
leadership. So let’s take a look.
עשר תקנות תיקן עזרא. Asara takkanot tikken Ezra. Ten תקנות takkanot עזרא
Ezra established.
שיקראו במנחה בשבת. Shekorei b'mincha b'shabbos. You read שבת מנחה Shabbos Mincha.
time. ושיקראו בשני ובחמישי. V’korei b’sheini v’chamishi. You read the תורה Torah
on, you know, Mondays and Thursdays. Okay, so very much if you
remember there’s a whole scene in עזרא Ezra where they have a
public reading of the תורה. Torah. And they actually not only have
a public reading, they have it in translation as well. You know,
so it's a teaching of the תורה Torah to the people. So
that modeling that idea of a regular reading and a learning of
תורה. Torah. Okay, that’s two. ודנין בשני ובחמישי. V’danin b’sheini v’chamishi. You
set up courts on Tuesdays and Thursdays.
ומכבסין בחמישי בשבת. U’mechabsin b’chamishi b’shabba. And you do laundry. Thursday is
the laundry day. Get everybody ready for
שבת. Shabbos Okay, ואוכלים שום בערב שבת. V’ochlim shum b’erev shabbos. You
eat garlic on Friday.
ושתהא אשה משכמת ואופה. V’shetei isha mashkemes v’ofah. When a woman is
going to be baking she should bake early in the morning, you
know bakers get up at 4:00 AM to bake. We’re going to
see what all this is about. ושתהא אשה חוגרת בסינר. V’shetei isha
chogeres b’sinar. A woman should wear a סינר sinar which is some
type of a seems like some type of an
undergarment. A סינר sinar which normally meant like an apron but some
anyway how do they translate it there?
Undergarment. But the note says an undergarment.
Yeah. It's more literally an apron. ושתהא אשה חופפת וטובלת. V’shetei isha
chofefes v’toveles. A woman should comb her hair before she goes into
the מקוה. mikvah. ושיהו רוכלים מחזירים בעיירות. V’sheyehu rochlin machzirin ba'ayaros. And
that the spice sellers and fragrance sellers should have a right to
travel in the various towns and people can't prevent them from coming
into their town. ותיקן טבילה לבעלי קריין. V’tikken tvila l’ba’alei kiryan. And
it's interesting it switches the language here. He established immersion for a
בעל קרי, ba'al keri, for somebody a man who had a seminal
emission. So let’s take a look. גמרא Gemara goes through these. שיקראו
במנחה בשבת, Shekorei b’mincha b’shabbos, משום יושבי קרנות. mishum yoshvei kranos. Because
of those people that sit in the קרן... keren... קרנות... kranos... what
is the קרנות? kranos? So רש"י Rashi says, you know, I always
thought it meant like the guys who hang out at the street
corners and they're smoking and whatever, you know, the good-for-nothings. You know,
so at least on שבת Shabbos. they have nowhere else to be
so they'll hear the reading of the תורה. Torah. But רש"י Rashi
actually gives a more positive emphasis to what יושבי קרנות yoshvei kranos
is. רש"י Rashi says יושבי קרנות yoshvei kranos are בני אדם bnei
adam says רש"י... Rashi... I'm sorry where’s רש"י... Rashi...
יושבי חנויות yoshvei chanuyos כל ימי החול. kol yemai hachol. They're basically
the storekeepers. They don't have time Mondays and Thursdays. Mondays and Thursdays
the reason everybody's coming to hear the תורה, Torah, it's because it's
a market day, but who's in the who's in the store? The
storekeepers, they never have time to come to hear the reading of
the תורה. Torah. Okay, so for רש״י Rashi it's like not a
bad thing, but you know, they're just they don't have any time
to do anything to, to do it. Okay, so they're going to
do it on Friday, at שבת מנחה. Shabbos Mincha, Question is why
do they not do it the next, like why do you still
need it Friday, you know, שבת Shabbos מנחה, Mincha they're going to
hear שבת Shabbos the תורה Torah reading, why do you need it
in the afternoon? But I guess the point is, they have so
little תורה Torah during the week, you give them another opportunity to
be learning תורה. Torah. Okay, maybe you also help give them some
anticipation of the next פרשה parsha for the coming week.
Okay, ושיקראו בשני ובחמישי v'shiyikru b'sheni u'v'chamishi so on Tuesdays and, on
Mondays and Thursdays. So the גמרא Gemara says, עזרא תיקן? Ezra tiken?
Was this עזרא Ezra established? הא מעיקרא הוא דתקנה. Ha me'ikara hu
detakna. This was established much earlier. דתניא, Detanya, it's taught in a
ברייתא, beraita, וילכו שלשת ימים במדבר ולא מצאו מים. Vayelechu shloshet yamim
bamidbar v'lo matzu mayim. They went three days and they did not
find
water. Okay, and the תורה Torah says that G-d showed משה, Moshe,
you know, a stick and he threw it in the water and
it made sweetened the water and there he made חוק ומשפט. chok
u'mishpat. Alright, so what's going on here? So the גמרא Gemara says,
דורשי רשומות אמרו, Dorshei rishumot amru, those that interpret hints in the
פסוקים pesukim say the following: אין מים אלא תורה, Ein mayim ela
Torah, meaning they give a sort of a, you know, a מדרש
midrashic read of the פסוקים. pesukim. Water means תורה. Torah. They didn't
find תורה. Torah. They went three days, you know, as the מהרש״א
Maharsha says, three days is the חזקה, chazakah, they were getting a
little established in their non-engagement of תורה. Torah. So שנאמר, Shene'emar, הוי
כל צמא לכו למים, Hoy kol tzame l'chu lamayim, come all you
thirsty, come to water. כיון שהלכו שלשה ימים בלא תורה, Keivan shehalchu
shlosha yamim b'lo Torah, they went three days without תורה, Torah, נלאו,
Nil'u, they became weary. You know, what does it mean? They, their
bodies were empty of a, you know, of a spiritual sustenance. So
that's why they started kvetching and complaining. Okay, and the מהרש״א Maharsha
says that's why the תורה Torah says ויראהו השם עץ, Vayorehu Hashem
etz, for it's like an עץ חיים, etz chayim, like that's the
מהרש״א Maharsha's דרשה drasha of the rest of the פסוק. pasuk. And
that's why שם שם לו חוק ומשפט, sham sam lo chok u'mishpat,
like he made him a law, you know. Anyway, the sense is
that you have to have a regular learning of תורה. Torah. עמדו
נביאים שביניהם, Amdu nevi'im shebeineihem, the prophets among them, which is משה
Moshe and אהרן Aaron and מרים, Miriam, stood among them, ותיקנו להם
שיהיו קוראים בשבת, v'tiknu lahem sheyihyu kor'im b'Shabbat, that they should regularly
read on שבת, Shabbos, ומפסיקין, u'mafsikin, meaning באחד בשבת, b'echad b'Shabbat, you
take a break on Sunday, וקוראים בשני, v'kor'im b'sheni, and then you
read on Monday, ומפסיקין
שלישי ורביעי, u'mafsikin shlishi v'revi'i, you break on Tuesday and Wednesday, וקוראים
בחמישי, v'kor'im b'chamishi, you read on Thursday, ומפסיקין ערב שבת, u'mafsikin erev
Shabbat, you break on Friday. Today, so almost there's a two-day, between
a one or a two-day gap between the readings, never three days
between readings, כדי שלא ילינו שלשה ימים בלא תורה, kdei shelo yalinu
shlosha yamim b'lo Torah, you shouldn't go three days without תורה. Torah.
So you see it wasn't עזרא, Ezra, it was established way back
by the time of the, you know, first thing they left מצרים.
Mitzrayim. So the גמרא Gemara says, נו מעיקרא תיקן חד
גברא תלתא פסוקי. No me'ikara tiken chad gavra tlata pesukei. No, okay,
עזרא Ezra expanded the תקנה. takkanah. Originally one person got an עליה
aliyah and he read three פסוקים. pesukim. אי נמי תלתא גברי תלתא
פסוקי, Ee nami tlata gavrei tlata pesukei, or three people came up
to the תורה Torah and each one read a פסוק pasuk for
a total of three פסוקים. pesukim. כנגד כהנים לויים וישראלים, K'neged Kohanim
Levi'im v'Yisraelim, representing כהן, Kohen, לוי, Levi, and ישראל. Yisrael. אתא איהו,
Ata ihu, עזרא Ezra came, תיקן תלתא גברי ועשרה
פסוקי, tiken tlata gavrei v'asara pesukei, three people should get עליות aliyot
and they should read a total of ten פסוקים. pesukim. כנגד עשרה
בטלנים, K'neged asara batlanim, opposite the ten people that are just בטלנים,
batlanim, are sort of like, are, you know, sitting around doing nothing,
meaning the ten people that are regularly in the שול shul in
order to be a regular presence and to make a מנין. minyan.
Okay, so, you know, that's like a מנין minyan man basically. So
רש״י Rashi says, if we look at רש״י, Rashi, עשרה בטלנים, asara
batlanim, רש״י Rashi says בני אדם כשרים בטלים ממלאכתם, b'nei adam kesherim
betelim m'mlachtam, they do nothing, they're good people, they're not like the
יושבי קרנות, Yoshvei Kranos, the opposite of the יושבי קרנות. Yoshvei Kranos.
They're standing around but they're standing around to be available for religious
purposes. לעסוק בצרכי ציבור לבוא קודם לבית הכנסת,
la'asok b'tzorchei tzibur lavo kodem l'veit hakeneset, that
they will, they're there to do anything of communal needs and to
be present in the שול shul to make a מנין. minyan. So
that's what he established that now according to that, it just means
that he established to read more פסוקים. pesukim. But it also seems
that it's reflecting the idea of this establishment, of this institution of
עשרה בטלנים, asara batlanim, right? And the whole idea that you would
have a sense of like a מנין. minyan. Like when they said,
you know, I mean it's, again, the גמרא Gemara is also, you
know, did was this really from the time of משה רבינו? Moshe
Rabbeinu? But within חז״ל'ס Chazal's you know, understanding that this was a
תקנה takkanah that went all the way back, do they imagine it?
It sounds like they imagined it also with a formal thing of
being called up to the תורה, Torah, one person x פסוקים, pesukim,
three people three פסוקים, pesukim, you know, but still one wonders, you
know, if the גמרא Gemara is also indicating that by the time
of עזרא Ezra it became more of a type of a synagogue
experience with a sense of a מנין minyan with ten people, like
was more somehow ritualized, you know? And that's sort of the extra
number for ten is not just more פסוקים pesukim but reflecting more
this מנין minyan and ritualized context. Okay, but anyway, those are two
תקנות takkanot about reading תורה Torah which clearly very much connect to
עזרא. Ezra. תוספות, Tosafos, by the way, asks a question and he
says why, you know, why Monday and Thursday? You could have made
it Tuesday and Thursday. You could have made it... Tuesday and Friday,
you know, like it's like, you know, there are a couple of
days you could have chosen. So תוספות Tosafot quotes a מדרש Midrash
that says that משה Moshe when he went up to get the
last לוחות, luchot, if the מדרש Midrash does the math and says
he went up on a Thursday and he came down on a
Monday. So those are days that are particularly times that are connecting
up to the תורה, Torah, עת רצון et ratzon says תוספות. Tosafot.
It's also like תוספות Tosafot says we have the מנהג minhag to
fast on, you know, they used to have fast days on Mondays
and Thursdays because it's times that God is desirous of our prayers
of course, you know, you don't really need that once people are
getting together for reading the תורה Torah on Mondays and Thursdays if
you're going to have fast days, you're going to do it on
times when everybody's getting together to read the תורה. Torah. And that
also ties into the next issue about the courts. דדייני בשני ובחמישי,
Dadnei b'shani b'chamishi, you would have courts on Mondays and Thursdays, דשכיחי
דאתו למקרא בספרא, dishchichei d'asu l'mikra besifra, because that's when people would
be around because people would come to hear the תורה Torah reading.
You know, it's an interesting question of like the chicken and the
egg, right? Did you have the courts on Mondays and Thursdays and
that's why you established them as תורה Torah reading days or did
you have the תורה Torah reading days and that's why they were
court days? But anyway, you know, it's a nice way, right? You
have these major days in which things get done that get people
together, right? Maybe they both תקנות takanot came at the same time.
Hey, let's do תורה Torah reading and court days and for one
reason or another, people will come for one, they'll be there for
the other, you know.
Or that's the market day.
I think that that he what he didn't formally establish the market,
but I think that that also arose from it. If those are
the days that people are all together.
Yeah, I
mean, it's true, you could speculate. You don't know. But you know,
it seems that these all sort of are going to come hand
in hand. By the way, תוספות Tosafot has an interesting question, תוספות
Tosafot says, you know, another place makes it sound that before עזרא,
Ezra, בית דין Beis Din sat every day. So he says, what
was עזרא Ezra doing? He was saying that they should sit less
frequently? So תוספות Tosafot says well, maybe before him they sat every
day only in major centers and he established that they would sit
on Mondays and Thursdays in all the villages, in all the towns.
But it's also possible, you know, sometimes if something is actually less
frequent it's actually more productive, right? You know, because then everybody focuses
their activities. It's sort of like why don't you just do the
laundry every day? You know, why don't you have any day sort
of do the laundry, you know? But if you have a focused
day it gets it done and it gets people focused on it.
Okay. So that's a... so ויהיו מכבסים בחמישי בשבת, v'yihyu mechabsim b'chamisha
b'shabbat, there we go, doing the laundry, משום כבוד השבת, mishum kevod
hashabbat, in order to honor שבת. Shabbat. ויהיו אוכלים שום בערב שבת,
V'yihyu ochlim shum b'erev Shabbat, and they would eat a garlic on
ערב שבת, erev Shabbat, משום עונה, mishum onah, for the purpose of
the מצוה mitzvah of having marital sex, relations. So therefore, we're going
to see in a minute that garlic is maybe it doesn't want
somebody to get too close to you, maybe you brush your teeth
afterwards, but it's supposed to be good for the semen, okay? And
therefore, it's a sumption that that's when people are going to be
having sex, because שנאמר והכתיב, shene'emar v'haksiv, the verse says, אשר פריו
יתן בעתו, asher piryo yiten b'ito, will give his fruit in the
right time, ואמר רב יהודה ואיתימא רב נחמן ואיתימא
רב כהנא ואיתימא רב יוחנן, v'amar Rav Yehuda v'isayma Rav Nachman v'isayma
Rav Kahana v'isayma Rav Yochanan, זה משמש מטתו
מערב שבת לערב שבת, zeh m'shamesh mitato m'erev Shabbat l'erev Shabbat, this
is somebody that has sex from Friday night to Friday night. Now,
the actual מצוה mitzvah of עונה onah like a standard frequency is
once a week, but here the גמרא Gemara specifically focuses on the
idea to do it on Friday night, presumably, I mean, some people
tie it into the idea of עונג שבת, Oneg Shabbat, or maybe
that's the time when people are not distracted by other things, you
know, but also, it should be noted that, you know, there were
sects, S-E-C-T-S, anyway, at that particularly in the בית שני Bayis Sheni
period that said it's forbidden to have sex on שבת. Shabbat. You
know, if it's a holy day, how could you do this most
physical type of an experience, sense, sensual type of experience? It's supposed
to be a spiritual and a religious day. So חז"ל Chazal very
much, I mean it really sort of showed, you know, said no,
on שבת Shabbat there's a מצוה mitzvah to have physical pleasure, עונג
שבת, Oneg Shabbat, sex, right? So it's like a really interesting question
of like a religious mindset, like an anti-asceticism type of an approach.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, תנו רבנן, Tano Rabbanan, it was
our Rabbis taught, חמישה דברים נאמרו בשום, chamisha devarim ne'emru b'shum, five
things are said about garlic: משביע, masbia, it makes you feel sated,
ומשחין, umashchin, it makes you feel like warm inside, ומצהיל פנים, umatzhil
panim, gives you a nice glow, ומרבה הזרע, umarbeh hazerah, increases the
semen, והורג כינים שבבני מעיים, v'horeg kinim shebibney me'ayim, destroys any lice
in your stomach, in okay intestinal bug,
bacteria, I guess, I don't know. ויש אומרים, V'yesh omrim, and some
say מכניס אהבה ומוציא את הקינאה, machnis ahavah umotzi et hakinah, because
it has all these other benefits, it just increases a sense of
makes you feel good all the all it makes you glow inside,
makes you love people, have this love, get rid of this jealousy,
great thing garlic. Okay, just don't get too close to people. Brush
your teeth. ושתהא אשה, V'satei ishah, garlic is one of those superfoods
by the way, it really is like I think you know what
the nutritionists say. ושתהא אשה משכמת ואופה, V'satei ishah mashkemet v'ofah, a
woman should go to bake bread she should do it early in
the morning, כדי שתהא פת מצויה לעניים, kedei shetihei pat m'tzuya la'aniyim,
because the poor people they're going around, so if everybody's baking bread,
you know, they'll have and bread is obviously, you know, very you
know the sort of what's it called the staple of life or
you know the staff of life, so bread so the poor people
will have will have bread. ושתהא אשה חוגרת בסינר, V'satei ishah chogeret
b'sinar, she should wear some undergarment type of an undergarment משום צניעותא,
mishum tzniutah, because of modesty, ושתהא אשה חופפת. v'shetehei ishah chofefet. ושתהא
אשה חופפת וטובלת, V'shetehe isha chofefet v'tovelet, she should comb her hair
before she goes to the מקוה. mikva. Now remember, we think of
מקוה mikva only as something that women do for נדה, niddah, but
in the time of עזרא, Ezra, everybody would be going to the
מקוה mikva for any type of impurity because of all the sacrifices
and the טהרות. taharos. So why does he only mention women? So
the clear answer is why do you think he only mentions women?
What do you think, David? Have a thought? 'Cause women have long
hair. So that's why, since this basically was about getting knots out
of hair and disentangling
it and whatever, so wouldn't the- if a man had long hair
or woman had short hair, it would apply to the person who
had the long hair, but nevertheless the basic תקנה takana was about
women because it was about combing your hair to get out any
types of knots. So the גמרא gemara says דאורייתא היא, d'oraisa hi,
that's a biblical obligation. דתניא, detanya, ורחץ את בשרו במים, v'rachatz et
besaro bamayim, you have to bathe your flesh with water. That's the
verse that speaks about immersion, ritual immersion. שלא יהא דבר חוצץ בין
בשרו למים, shelo yihe davor chotzetz bein b'saro lamayim, it has to
be your flesh has to be directly in contact with the water.
That's your flesh. את בשרו, et besaro, but it says את, et,
your flesh, but it uses the extra word את. et. את הטפל
לבשרו, et hatafel l'besaro, something that is connected to the flesh, which
is what? ומאי ניהו שיער, umai nihu sear, that your hair has
to be directly in contact with the water. So of course you
have to comb out your hair to get out any types of
things that might be in the way. That's a מצוה, mitzvah, the
תורה Torah demands that's what טבילה tevilah is. So גמרא gemara says
no, ומאי ניהו שיער? umai nihu sear? דאורייתא לעיוני, d'oraisa l'yunay, biblically
it's enough just to inspect your hair, I guess with your hands.
דילמא מקטר, dilma miktar, maybe there's a knot,
אינמי מאוס מידי, inami m'ose midi, or maybe some type of disgusting
thing is in your hair, משום חציצה, mishum chatzitza, that that'll be
an obstruction and won't make a good going into the מקוה mikva
good. ואיהו תיקן חפיפה, va-hu tikein chafifa, and he said that's not
enough to just run your fingers through your hair or do some
type of a visual inspection, you actually have to comb your hair.
Now there's an interesting point that תוספות tosfos discusses, which is we
have something that before women go to the מקוה, mikva, they do
a whole process of sitting in the bath and whatever and preparing
and bathing their body and inspecting every part of their body and
scrubbing themselves. So תוספות tosfos says that it seems from the גמרא
gemara obviously that that was an ancient practice, there's evidence in the
גמרא gemara that they were doing that, but that it does not
seem that it was formally part of the תקנה takana of עזרא.
Ezra. That the תקנה takana of עזרא Ezra because your body you
could just inspect and see if there's something, but the hair is
harder, it gets knotted, it's harder to see and so on, so
that the תקנה takana of עזרא Ezra was really about the hair,
the body was not a תקנה takana although that obviously practice of
doing a bathing and an inspection of it came later. Even by
the hair the interesting question is is it just combing or is
it washing and combing? So there's some interesting questions around that.
Okay, ושיסו רוכלים מחזירים בעיירות, v'sheyihu rochlim machzirin ba'ayarot, and the fragrance
sellers would go around into the villages. This is interesting because this
is the one thing that doesn't sound so ritual related, but we'll
see it sort of is. משום תכשיטי נשים, mishum tachshitay nashim, in
order to sell women various jewelry or
fragrances, כדי שלא יתגנו על בעליהן, k'day shelo yitganu al ba'aleihen, so
that they should not be found be disgusting to their husbands or
their husbands should desire them. So it's very different than the property
rights, the more communal look, this is more private look. But it's
also similar to the סינר sinar issue before, the סינר, sinar, the
modesty, a concern sort of about family life.
ותיקן טבילה לבעלי קריין, v'tikein tevilah l'ba'alei kerayin, and he said that
a man who had a seminal emission has to go to the
מקוה. mikva. So גמרא gemara says דאורייתא הוא, d'oraisa hu, that's biblical.
דכתיב, dechtiv, ואיש כי תצא ממנו שכבת זרע ורחץ
במים את כל בשרו, v'ish ki tetze mimenu shichvat zera v'rachatz bamayim
et kol besaro, if a man has a seminal emission he has
to go to the מקוה mikva in order to be pure. So
the תורה Torah says that's what you need to do to be
pure. So גמרא gemara says no, דאורייתא הוא לתרומה וקדשים, d'oraisa hu
l'teruma v'kodashim, according to the תורה Torah sure that you're impure and
without going to the מקוה, mikva, but what's the implications of being
impure according to the תורה? Torah? That you can't touch or eat
תרומה terumah or you can't touch or eat sacrifices. So that of
course that's true. ואיהו תיקן אפילו
לדברי תורה, va-hu tikein afilu l'divrei Torah, he said that he really
wasn't מתקן metaken going to the מקוה, mikva, what he really was
מתקן metaken was that if you're בעל קרי, ba'al keri, you can't
learn תורה Torah until you've gone to the מקוה, mikva, you can't
דאווען daven until you've gone to the מקוה. mikva. So you might
know for example that some חסידים chassidim have a practice of every
morning going to the מקוה. mikva. So where this comes from, if
you didn't know where it comes from, I'm going to tell you
now. Where this comes from is because this
גמרא gemara says you can't learn תורה, Torah, you can't דאווען daven
without going to the מקוה. mikva. So what do you do? So
anytime a man has had sex with his wife or has had
a seminal emission, he would have to go to the מקוה mikva
that morning. Of course, what do you then go look in the
morning and you see men going to the מקוה, mikva, you start
wondering what were they, what,
you connect the dots. So therefore it became the practice to just
go to the מקוה mikva every morning so nobody wonders what you
were doing that night before, and because that you have to, or
else how are you supposed to דאווען, daven, how are you supposed
to learn תורה? Torah? So the thing is, but so why doesn't
everybody have to do that? So if you take a look at
תוספות, tosfos, ואיהו תיקן טבילה אפילו לדברי תורה, va-hu tikein tevilah afilu
l'divrei Torah, תוספות tosfos says לא קיימא לן הכי, lo kayma lan
hachi, we don't rule this way, אלא כרבי יהודה בן בתירא... ela
k'Rabbi Yehuda ben Beseira... דברי תורה אין מקבלין טומאה. divrei Torah ein
mikablin tumah. The words of תורה Torah do not accept, cannot become
טמא. tamei. He basically overrode עזרא Ezra's תקנה. takkana. And that gets
into this whole question though, because if עזרא Ezra makes a תקנה,
takkana, what some later אמורא Amora has the power to override this
תקנה? takkana? But then it's also evident that people were not really
able to keep by this תקנה. takkana. So it becomes a תקנה
takkana that most of the community couldn't abide by, but that led
to interesting questions. So there's definitely some places that still kept to
this תקנה. takkana. And that's why, you know, this practice came up
amongst some to go to the מקוה mikvah every single morning. Okay,
so then the גמרא Gemara says,
now we move on from עזרא Ezra to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. We're listing
ten things, right? So this is those are תקנות takkanot and here
are going to be more like laws. עשרה דברים נאמרו בירושלים. asarah
devarim ne'emru b'Yerushalayim. Ten laws were said relating to Jerusalem. אין הבית
חלוט בה. ein bayis chalut ba. A house cannot become a מצורע
metzora house in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. ואין מביאה עגלה ערופה. v'ein m'via egla
arufa. If there's a dead body of a murdered victim outside of
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you do not bring the עגלה ערופה, egla arufa, you
know, the calf that you break the neck for ירושלים. Yerushalayim. ואינה
נעשית עיר הנדחת. v'eino na'asis ir nidachas. If the entire city worships
עבודה זרה, avoda zara, you do not wipe out the entire city.
ואין מטמא בנגעים... v'ein m'tamei b'nega'im... oh I'm sorry when I jumped
ahead, חלוט בה chalut ba was not מצורע. metzora. ואין מטמא בנגעים
v'ein m'tamei b'nega'im means that a house does not become a house
of צרעת tzara'as in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. אין הבית חלוט בה ein bayis
chalut ba means that if somebody sells a house in ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
so in all other walled cities, if it's not bought back within
the year, it becomes permanently owned by the buyer, whereas in ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, you have the right to buy back the house until the
יובל. yovel. Okay, so that's what אין הבית חלוט בה ein bayis
chalut ba means. ואין מוציאין בה זיזין וגזוזטראות. v'ein motzin bah gizizin
v'guztra'os. You do not have like beams, you know, coming out from
the rooftops and balconies protruding over the streets in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. ואין
עושין בה אשפתות. v'ein osin bah ashpotos. You do not make garbage
dumps in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. ואין עושין בה כבשונות. v'ein osin bah kivshonot.
You do not make places of kilns of firing pottery or whatever
in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. ואין עושין בה גנות ופרדסות. v'ein osin bah gannot
u'pardesot. This might be the most surprising one. You don't make gardens
and orchards in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. חוץ מגנות ורדין, chutz mi'gannot verdin, except
for
gardens of roses,
which was the practice from the early times of the early prophets.
I think there's a question whether ורד vered really means a rose,
because the פסוק pasuk in שיר השירים, Shir HaShirim,
his lips are like שושנים. shoshanim. For us a שושן shoshan is
a lily, right? Isn't that how we translate שושן? shoshan? Anyway, but
it doesn't make sense. Your lips are like roses, not your lips
are like lilies. So I'm not sure that ורד vered originally meant
rose. How do they translate ורד vered there? Rose gardens?
They
said except for maintained a garden of roses.
Roses, yeah.
Okay and also the רש"י Rashi said that was a specific place...
Oh, it wasn't rose gardens in general, it was a name of
a place...
it was the name of a garden...
Oh, yeah. That's interesting. Does that what this רש"י Rashi
say? כך
שמה והיא היתה צריכה לקטורת. kach shema ve-hi hayta tzricha le-ktoret. Yeah,
I guess כך שמה kach shema makes it sound like it's a
name place. That's interesting. Okay. Anyway, רש"י Rashi says the reason was
that they needed it for the making of the קטורת. ketoret.
ואין מגדלין בה תרנגולים. v'ein m'gadlin bah tarnagolim. They would not, you
don't raise chickens. ואין מלינין בה את המת. v'ein m'linin bah es
ha-meis. You do not let a dead body stay overnight. Normally, you
know, there's a biblical prohibition to let a body stay overnight, but
if it's needed for the honor of the dead body, you're allowed
to do it, but in ירושלים Yerushalayim they would not.
ואין הבית חלוט בה. v'ein bayis chalut ba.
A house does not become fully sold over to the buyer. The
seller can always buy it back. דכתיב, diksiv, וקם הבית אשר לו
חומה, ve-kama bayis asher lo choma, and a house that's in a
place that has a wall, לקונה אותו לדורותיו, la-koneh oto l'dorotav, to
what it purchased
for future generations. וקסבר לא נתחלקה ירושלים לשבטים. ve-kasavar lo nitchalka Yerushalayim
l'shvatim. And this is going to be the theme here. ירושלים Yerushalayim
was
not divided, was a national city... It was not the property of
any one tribe. And therefore,
normally there's a פסוק pasuk that makes it clear that a certain
law applies to a city that is considered to be possessed by
a particular tribe. But I don't exactly see the word they're darshaning
it from here. Maybe the word לדורותיו, l'dorotav, for future generations, that
suggests a sense of permanent
ownership. Whereas ירושלים Yerushalayim fundamentally, you know, is a national city, and
therefore this law does not apply. ואינה מביאה עגלה ערופה, Ve'einah mevia
eglah arufah, you do not bring a, you know, if there's a
dead body, a murder victim, you don't bring this calf that you
break its neck, דכתיב, dechitiv, כי ימצא חלל באדמה אשר ה'
אלקיך נותן לך לרשתה, ki yimatzei chalal ba'adamah asher Hashem Elokecha noten
lecha lerishtah, if you find a corpse, a murder victim,
on the ground which Hashem has given you to inherit, meaning so
if ירושלים Yerushalayim was not divided among the tribes, again that's the
word, God has given it to you for to inherit, so that
has a sense of that it's owned to be passed down by
one tribe and by its owners to the people who own it
to like their descendants. And this remains in some sense, again, you
wonder what does that mean? People didn't buy property exactly how things
worked, but nevertheless conceptually this isn't owned by anybody and therefore it's
not that God has given you לרשתה lerishtah to inherit. All right.
ואינה נעשית עיר הנדחת, Ve'einah na'asit ir hanidachat, it does not become
a city that would get totally burned out if the people worship
עבודה זרה, avoda zara,
דכתיב dechitiv עירך, irecha, your city, which has that sense again of
being owned and possessed. ירושלים לא נתחלקה לשבטים, Yerushalayim lo nitchalka leshvatim,
it wasn't divided amongst the tribes. And you know, it wasn't given
over to any one tribe. ואינה מטמאה בנגעים, Ve'einah metama bene'ga'im, it
doesn't become טמא tamei if one of the houses gets צרעת, tzara'at,
like this spot, דכתיב dechitiv ונתתי נגע צרעת בבית ארץ
אחוזתכם, venatati nega tzara'at beveit eretz achuzatchem, I will give it in
a house of the land that you have taken possession of. ירושלים
לא נתחלקה לשבטים, Yerushalayim lo nitchalka leshvatim, and again this was not
given over to any one tribe. ואין מוציאין בה זיזין וגזוזטראות, Ve'ein
motzi'in bah zizin u'gezustra'ot, so all those are more formal exceptions. Now
we're going to hear some practical things. You don't have these protruding
beams or balconies over the street מפני אהל הטומאה, mipnei ohel hatuma,
because if a dead body, some dead thing on the street, right,
a dead corpse, and then if you have a long
balcony it'll transfer it to people that are very distant from it
and in ירושלים Yerushalayim where all the sacrifices are, you do not
want to increase the amount of the spreading of the טומאה. tuma.
There was actually a time of a like some פוסקים poskim wrote
about the fact in certain towns there was a Jewish street and
all the Jews lived on like this one street and there were
these balconies that came out from, you know, that were like if
you imagine like a row of houses, right? It wasn't separate houses.
It was like a big row, attached row of houses, and these
balconies protruding. Anytime there was a dead body in any one house
the טומאה tuma would go into all the houses. It would spread
under the balcony and then go into the windows. So like a
whole big question about how to deal with those cases.
Okay, so
okay. ומשום דלא ליצקו עולי רגלים, u'mishum delo litzku olei regalim, and
another practical thing, if you have protruding things in the street and
people are coming in and they're traveling, there's
a lot of
visitors that come to ירושלים Yerushalayim for the רגל regel and all
of that, so they'd be walking and they'd be banging their head
or they'll be riding on a horse and banging their heads on
these protrusions. ואין עושין בה אשפתות, Ve'ein osin bah ashpatot, you don't
make garbage dumps, משום שקצים, mishum shekatzim, you're just thinking maybe it's
disgusting, you know, ירושלים Yerushalayim is the this whatever this international city
as we just said but no, national city. משום שקצים, Mishum shekatzim,
because of like rodents, because the problem is it attracts rodents and
rodents, dead rodents, are a source of טומאה. tuma. ואין עושין בה
כבשונות, Ve'ein osin bah kivshonot, you don't make these kilns, you know,
these places for firing up pottery, משום קוטרא, mishum kutra, because of
the smoke, you know, and it's bad air, you know, the air
pollution. ואין עושין בה גגות גנות ופרדסין, Ve'ein osin bah gagot gannot
u'fardesin, you do not make gardens or orchards. That's the curious one.
משום סירחא, mishum sircha, because those things, you know, even though they
might look beautiful, they give off a stink. I think like an
apple orchard in particular. Ever been in an apple orchard? Apparently it's
like a really bad smell. Anyway, and also maybe because of all
the fertilizer it requires. ואין מגדלין בה תרנגולים, Ve'ein migdalin bah tarnegolim,
you don't have chickens משום קדשים, mishum kodashim, because the chickens go
and they and they go and they, you know,
they they peck around, they move little things and they'll bring like
a little piece of bone and they'll put it on your, you
know, and they'll and they'll get your תרומה, terumah, your sacrifices טמא.
tamei. ואין מלינין בה את המת, Ve'ein malinin bah et hamet, and
you don't let a dead body sleep over. גמרא, Gemara, that's just
a tradition. We don't actually have a reason for it, but you
know obviously it must connect to the sense of the קדושה kedusha
and the טהרה, taharah, the purity of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. They should have
just made a תקנה takanah that you're not allowed to die in
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. I don't know. Okay, now we move on, so that
was a nice list of ten things, and now we go back
to the משנה mishna that speaks about things that you're not allowed
to do in general. It started with in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
for the sake of the Jewish community in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
but then it goes on in other types of things like it
starts with raising, you know, grazing animals, but then it moves on
to other things. So let's now look.
אין מגדלין חזירין בכל מקום. Ein migdalin chazirin bechol makom. So you
can't raise grazing animals in the land of Israel but you can't
raise pigs anywhere. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, our rabbis taught, כשצרו בית
חשמונאי זה על זה, kshetzaru beit chashmonai zeh al zeh, when they
a war of. of the different families of the חשמונאים Hashmonaim and
that one was laying siege to the other.
הורקנוס היה הורקנוס מבפנים, Horkanus hayah Horkanus mibifnim, הורקנוס Horkanus was inside
Jerusalem, ואריסטובלוס מבחוץ, veAristobulus mibachutz, and אריסטובלוס Aristobulus was on the outside
laying siege to Jerusalem. בכל יום היו משלשלים להם בקופה דינרים Bechol
yom hayu meshalshelim lahem bekupa dinarim and every day though, you know,
everybody was good פרום frum Jews even though they were at civil
war, so they would lower down from Jerusalem a basket with דינרים
dinarim in it, with these gold coins, or silver coins, והיו מעלין
להם תמידים vehayu ma'alin lahem temidim and they would send up, you
know, sheep to be used as the daily sacrifice. היה שם זקן
אחד, Hayah sham zaken echad, there was one elder among them, שהיה
מכיר בחכמת יוונית. shehayah makir bechochmat yevanit. He knew Greek wisdom. Now
I never understood this because what he's about to say has nothing
to do with Greeks, but anyway he knew Greek wisdom. אמר להם,
Amar lahem, he said to them, כל זמן שעוסקים בעבודה אין נמסרים
בידכם, kol zeman sheoskim ba'avodah ein nimtsarim beyadechem, as long as they
are able to continue doing the divine sacrifice, God won't let them,
you know, be conquered by you. Again, like that's such a like
Jewish religious type of a thing to be saying, I don't really
understand the חכמת יוונית chochmat yevanit point of this.
Yeah, what does the note say?
He was a cryptic allusive sign language which was
only
spoken by the members of the royal household, right, which
couldn't be
deciphered by the masses.
It was like a code, right, so that other people couldn't understand.
Yeah, so that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say later,
that it was some type of a, you know, some type of
like a coded language. But again, like it doesn't still fully explain
it. Like, you know, why can't he say hey we need to
have a little private consultation, right? And the whole word חכמת יוונית
chochmat yevanit sounds like it's some like it's some like field of
of of wisdom, it doesn't feel like it's just coded speech.
But yeah, maybe
referring
to
the Greek, you know, the Hellenists that were fighting. Yeah, but then
but that isn't that a Hellenistic type of a perspective on things?
You know, as long as you're doing the worship, maybe it is,
I don't know, I don't know. I mean, the Greeks believed in
their gods and they believed, you know, so I there's something...
It could be the battle between the Hellenists and
the...
Oh, I don't...
That's an interest... I don't know enough. There's a lot of historical
stuff about this which, you know, in Josephus and elsewhere, whatever, I
just don't know all I just... I'd have to לחזור lachzor it.
I don't know off the top of my head. But I don't
know specifically if it was between between the religious and the Hellenists.
I think it was more just a power play, but I'm not
sure, I don't remember. You might be right.
אמר להם, Amar lahem, he said to them, I'll take a look,
cause maybe you're right, maybe that would tie into the חכמת יוונית.
chochmat yevanit. That's what I mean. Yeah, so let me let me
take a look about that. אמר להם, Amar lahem, he said to
them, כל זמן שעוסקים בעבודה אין נמסרים בידכם. kol zeman sheoskim ba'avodah
ein nimtsarim beyadechem. למחר, Lemachar, the next day, שילשלו דינרים בקופה, shilshelu
dinarim bekupa, so they lower down the דינרים, dinarim, והעלו להם חזיר,
vehe'elu lahem chazir, they sent up not a sheep but but but
a pig. כיון שהגיע לחצי החומה, Keivan shehigia lachatzi hachomah, he got
got to half the half the wall, נעץ צפרניו בחומה, na'atz tzipornav
bachomah, the pig stuck its claws into the wall, you know, because
רש''י Rashi says that's what pigs do if you try to שלעפ
shlep them somewhere they don't want to go, ונזדעזעה ארץ ישראל ארבע
מאות פרסה על ארבע מאות פרסה, venizda'aze'ah Eretz Yisrael arba me'ot parsa
al arba me'ot parsa, the entire land of Israel, which was assumed
to be 400 parsangs by 400 parsangs, it shook like by, you
know, the the not the heresy, what's the word, the blasphemy, as
it were, you know, about the act, the sacrilege, that's the word.
Okay, you know, here it is, like, you know, not only are
you not sending up the sheep, you're doing this this this pig
or whatever. באותה שעה אמרו, Be'otah sha'ah amru, at that time they
said, ארור האיש שיגדל חזירים, arur ha'ish sheyegadel chazirim, cursed be the
person who raises pigs, וארור האדם שילמד את בנו חכמת יוונית, ve'arur
ha'adam sheyelamed et beno chochmat yevanit, cursed be the person who teaches
his son Greek wisdom. ועל אותה שעה שנינו, Ve'al otah sha'ah shaninu,
and it was at that time in Jewish history that the following
משנה Mishnah was taught, מעשה, ma'aseh, that there was a time, says
this משנה במנחות, Mishnah beMenachot, שבא עומר מגנות הצריפין, sheba omer migannot
hatzrifin, they had to bring the עומר omer from a distant place,
from the gardens of צריפין, Tzrifin, ושתי הלחם מבקעת עין סוכר, ushtei
halechem mibik'at Ein Socher, and the שתי הלחם shtei halechem from this
place, the valley of עין סוכר, Ein Socher, because they were not
since they were besieged, they did not have enough local wheat in
order to bring these sacrifices. So anyway, that's like a side comment.
Now תוספות Tosafot asks an important question.
He asks a couple of questions. First תוספות לא יגדלו חזירים Tosafot
lo yegadelu chazirim says, ואם תאמר תיפוק דאסור לעשות סחורה בכל דברים
הטמאים, ve'im tomar teipuki de'assur la'asot schora bechol devarim hateme'im, he says
normally we have a principle that you are not allowed to have
a business with non-kosher food items. Meaning you can if if you're
like going fishing and in your net you catch a, you know,
some type of a, you know, lobsters by accident but you were
fishing for tuna, you can sell the lobsters, but you're not supposed
to have a business in lobsters, in non-kosher food items. So how
here, he says, why do you say you shouldn't raise pigs? It
sounds like, you know, you're having a pig farm, you're doing this
as a business. Why isn't that forbidden? So why did you need
this special תקנה? takanah? And according to some, it might even be
based on a biblical verse. So תוספות Tosafot says, it's only when
you're doing it for food, like you're doing it as a food
item. But you could be raising חזירים, chazirim, he says there could
be other purposes, apparently you could be doing them for
their... hides
and for their or for their fat like you know to use
so but although to me it's like a little funny because it
seems like you know you wouldn't raise the there'd be a lot
be wasted if you were just be interested in the hides and
the fat of the pig. I mean I guess pig's fat is
definitely has a lot of uses but what are you going to
do I mean that's lard isn't lard pig fat? I think so.
But anyway but that's anyway that's תוספות's Tosafot answer. The other answer
would be that that's a that's a rabbinic law and that law
hadn't been passed yet. But nevertheless it's still interesting why did the
משנה Mishnah have to say it? Because by the time of the
משנה Mishnah that law had already been in place that you're not
allowed to do focused business on you know with non-kosher items. So
that's one question. And then the other question תוספות Tosafot has is
that we already actually in an earlier war they had made a
גזירה gezerah they had said that you know that you couldn't at
the time of the at the end of בית ראשון Bayis Rishon
apparently according to one גמרא Gemara they said one minute.
No I'm sorry בית שני Bayis Sheni excuse me Titus you know
I'm sorry I'm sorry I'm sorry no that's the one. It's the
reverse. Here this says that they had a curse from the time
of this the חשמונאים Chashmonaim to do חכמה יוונית chochma yevanis but
another גמרא Gemara says that at the time of the wars of
the חורבן churban of the destruction of the second בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash they made a prohibition to learn חכמה יוונית. chochma yevanis. So
תוספות Tosafot says what's the story? So he says well here was
just a curse if you wanted to do it and get cursed
that was up to you but by the time of the חורבן
churban of the destruction of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash there it
actually became a formal rabbinic you know prohibition. The point is there
seems to be a certain amount of redundancy and overlap in some
of these issues. Okay so now
so we really are done so we'll end here I guess and
we will pick up with this tomorrow. Okay maybe by then I'll
have an answer to you about whether this was a war between
Hellenists and you know religionists. Okay. Very good.
Here's the two yeah both חשמונאים Chashmonaim so I don't know.
Yeah right but you know there were different parts of the חשמונאים
Chashmonaim so maybe you're right.
So can you go fishing with a worm?
Sure. You're not doing business in selling worms.
Right.
You can't be in the business of selling fishing worms. You can
be in the business of selling fishing supplies and as part of
that means you have to stock your store with worms but you
know basically right that's a different type of a story.
Thanks.
Yeah.
We're caught up. We are caught up.
I'm gonna close this it might rain.
Oh sure thanks.
רבא Rava says לפי שאין עדים מצויין לקיימו, lefi she'ein edim metzuyin
lekaymo, because there are no עדים edim available to
confirm the signatures. The גמרא Gemara then explores the
differences between these two reasons. For example, if
the גט get was brought from one place to
another
within
ארץ
ישראל,
Eretz
Yisrael,
would
the
same rule apply? According
to רבה, Rabbah, since the people in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael are
experts in the הלכה, halacha, they
wouldn't
need
to say it.
But
according
to רבא, Rava, if witnesses are
not available, it might still be necessary. These discussions help us understand
the importance of witnesses and intention in the process
of a גט. get. ברוך אתה ה' אלהינו מלך העולם אשר
קדשנו במצותיו וצונו לעסוק בדברי תורה. Baruch atah Adonai Elokeinu melech haolam
asher kidshanu bemitzvosav vetzivanu laasok bedivrei Torah. אמן.
Amen. So do you know what I mean about the ones that
are shorter ones, shorter clips? Yeah. Are you still producing them? Yeah,
I'm staying with the old ones, but it's very popular for sure.
Okay, thank you, good luck. Thank you. Alright, good morning. Good morning
everybody. Good morning. Okay, please take out your
גמרות. Gemoros. We are starting דף כג עמוד א.
daf chaf-gimmel amud aleph. We're on
the new משנה. Mishna. Actually, the גמרא Gemara right after the משנה.
Mishna. The first word is אמר. amar. We're going
to be talking about
the סוגיא sugya of יאוש שלא מדעת. yeiush shelo mida'at. This
is a very famous מחלוקת machlokes between אביי Abaye and רבא.
Rava. Does it count as יאוש yeiush if the person doesn't know
yet? Let's see the גמרא. Gemara. אמר amar אביי Abaye יאוש שלא
מדעת yeiush shelo mida'at הוי יאוש havy yeiush ורבא אמר לא הוי
יאוש. veRava amar lo
havy yeiush בדבר שיש בו סימן bedavar sheyeish bo siman כולי עלמא
לא פליגי kulei alma lo paligi דלא הוי יאוש dilo havy yeiush
ואף על גב דשמעיניה דמיאש לבסוף ve'af al gav deshameinih demiya'ash levasof
לא הוי יאוש. lo havy yeiush. כי קמיפלגי ki kamipalgi בדבר שאין
בו סימן. bedavar she'ein bo siman. אביי אמר הוי יאוש Abaye amar
havy yeiush מהשתא הוי יאוש mehashta havy yeiush כיון דכי ידע
דנפל מיניה מיאש keivan deki yada denafal mineih miya'ash מעיקרא נמי הוי
יאוש me'ikara nami havy yeiush ורבא אמר veRava amar לא הוי יאוש
lo havy yeiush. עד דכי ידע דנפל מיניה. ad deki yada denafal
mineih. What's the point of contention? אביי Abaye says since the owner
will eventually find out and be מיאש, miya'ash, we can say that
retroactively it's as if he's already given up hope. Because the reality
of the situation is that the object is gone and he can't
get it back. רבא Rava says no, you need actual knowledge. You
need the person to actually
give up hope in his mind. Until that happens, it's still his.
So if you find it before he knows,
you're taking something that still belongs to him.
This has huge implications for השבת אבידה. hashavat aveidah. Let
us begin the third פרק perek of בבא בתרא, Bava Basra, חזקת
הבתים. Chazakas Habatim. Let's look at the first דף daf in the
פרק, perek, דף כח עמוד א. daf kaf ches amud aleph. The
משנה mishna says, חזקת הבתים, chazakas habatim, the חזקה chazakah for houses,
בורות, boros, שיחין, shichin, ומערות, ume'aros, pits, ditches, and caves, and שובכות,
shovachos, dove-cotes, מרחצאות, merchatza'os, bathhouses, בית הבד, beis habad, olive presses,
בית השלחין, beis hashlachin, an irrigated field, and עבדים, avadim, slaves,
and anything that makes fruit continuously, חזקתם שלוש
שנים מיום ליום. chazakasam shalosh shanim miyom leyom. Their חזקה chazakah is
three years from day to day. A שדה
הבעל, sadeh habaal, which is a rain-fed field, חזקתם שלוש שנים ואינן
מיום ליום. chazakasam shalosh shanim ve'einan miyom leyom. Its חזקה chazakah is
three years but not necessarily from day to day. רבי ישמעאל Rebbe
Yishmael says three months in the first year, three months in the
last year, and one
year in the middle, altogether eighteen months. רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva
says one month in the beginning,
one month in the end,
and a year in the
middle, altogether fourteen months. The גמרא gemara asks, what is the reason
for שלוש שנים? shalosh shanim? Why specifically three years? The answer given
is that for up to three years, a
person is careful with his שטר. shtar. After three years,
a person is not careful. Therefore, the בעלים baalim should have made
a מחאה. mecha'ah. If they did not make a
מחאה mecha'ah within those three years, the person who
is currently in the field is believed that he bought it from
them. The גמרא gemara later discusses what happens if
one of those years was שביעית. shvi'is. In שביעית, shvi'is, the fruits
are הפקר hefker and everyone is allowed to eat them. Can you
still
have a חזקה chazakah during שביעית? shvi'is? The משנה mishna seems to
say that שביעית shvi'is does count because even though
the fruits are הפקר, hefker, the owner is still in possession of
the land and
the בעלים baalim still had the opportunity to protest. Since they did
not, the חזקה chazakah is valid. This is
an important הלכה halacha in the laws of property and ownership. Hello.
Hey, how you doing? No, it's good. Yeah.
Sure. I mean, it's mine is not you
don't have to do it at all. It's
just a statistic. It's not real, nobody gets
it. It has no legal weight. And what
it is, is it's a it's a financial commitment to make sure
that you know you'll see that your kids get to the חופה
chuppah and if not that you will be suffer certain financial penalties.
I mean right now the financial penalties are
down. But so, if the family want to, I'm happy to do
both parents. It never came up that they
wanted to just do the mothers or that that was
a possibility, but there'd be no problem with doing
that. Exactly. Exactly. Yep. Yep. Okay, sure. Just
out of curiosity, is it that you just
want to create balance or that the fathers for some reason don't
want to participate? Nature. Nature, nature. Got it, got it, got it.
Yeah, why not? Why not have one ceremony that's all, all about
the women? Sounds lovely. Yep, yep, very good. All right, יישר כח,
shkoiach, thank you. Talk to you later, bye-bye. When a person wants
to buy a ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, תפילין,
Tefillin, or מזוזות, Mezuzot, the גמרא Gemara in שבת, Shabbat, דף קלג,
Daf Kuf Lamed Gimmel, page 133b, says זה קלי ואנווהו. Zeh Keli
Ve'anvehu. This teaches us the concept of התנאה לפניו במצוות. Hitna'eh Lefanav
Bemitzvot. Make a beautiful סוכה, Sukkah, a beautiful לולב, Lulav, beautiful ציצית,
Tzitzit, and write a beautiful ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. And the גמרא
Gemara in בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, page 9b, says עד שליש במצוה.
Ad Shlish Bemitzvah. One should spend up
to a third to beautify the מצוה. Mitzvah. The גמרא Gemara asks,
is it מלגיו Milgav or מלבר? Milbar? מלגיו Milgav means from
the inside, or מלבר, Milbar, from the outside. The הלכה Halacha is
מלבר, Milbar, a third on top of the original price.
Good morning. We're continuing the משנה ברורה. Mishna Berurah. This morning's שיעור
shiur is sponsored by the Melohn family as a זכות zechut for
a רפואה שלמה refuah sheleimah for שלמה זלמן בן פעשא
בתיה. Shlomo Zalman ben Pesha Basya. May he have
a רפואה שלמה refuah sheleimah בתוך שאר חולי ישראל. betoch shear cholei
Yisrael. We're
on
page תרפ"ט taf-resh-peh-tet in the משנה ברורה Mishna Berurah at the top
of the second column. We're in סימן תפ"ט siman taf-peh-tet סעיף ב.
seif bet. The מחבר mechaber
says המקדים
לקרות קריאת
שמע
עם הציבור מבעוד
יום.
hamakdim likrot keri'at shema im hatzibbur mibiod
yom.
We're talking about a case where a person is מתפלל מעריב mitpallel
Maariv early.
Many places in the summer,
they have an early מנין minyan and they're מתפלל
מעריב mitpallel Maariv well before nightfall. It might be before
שקיעה, shkiah, it might be after שקיעה shkiah but before
צאת הכוכבים. tzet hakochavim. It's during what we call פלג
המנחה. Plag HaMincha. He already said קריאת שמע, keri'at shema,
he's already davened שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. Now they're
going to count ספירה. sefirah. The מחבר mechaber says he
should count then with the ציבור tzibbur without a ברכה. beracha. Why
does he count then? Because if he waits until he gets home,
he might forget to count altogether. So count now, it's better to
count now than to forget. If he is afraid that he's going
to forget, he should count in שול shul without a ברכה. beracha.
Then, later on when it's definitely night, when it's צאת הכוכבים, tzet
hakochavim, then he should count again and this time he counts with
a ברכה. beracha. The משנה ברורה Mishna Berurah in סעיף
קטן ו
seif
katan vav points out that even though we
have an opinion of the בה"ג, Ba'ag, the בעל הלכות גדולות, Baal
Halachot Gedolot, that
if a person counts
during the day, he's יוצא, yotze, we don't follow
that opinion לכתחילה. lechatchila. The reason is because of the requirement of
תמימות. temimot. The תורה Torah says שבע שבתות תמימות תהיינה. sheva shabbatot
temimot tihyeyna. If you count when it's still day, the day hasn't
begun yet, so it's not
considered a complete day, it's not תמימות. temimot. Therefore, you
have to count at night. If he counted
during בין השמשות, bein hashmashot, then there's a problem of a ספק.
safek. Since ספירת העומר sefirat ha'omer nowadays is דרבנן, derabbanan, we would
say ספק דרבנן לקולא safek derabbanan lekula and he would be יוצא
yotze בדיעבד. bedieved. However, even though he's יוצא, yotze, he doesn't make
a ברכה beracha because we have a rule of ספק ברכות להקל.
safek berachot lehakel. We don't make a ברכה beracha when there
is any doubt. Tonight I want to focus on
a small section of the גמרא Gemara that we skipped over during
the last few weeks as we
were working on the eighth chapter of מסכת שבת Maseches Shabbos and
it deals
with the question of the source of the concept that
something like clothing or jewelry
being worn in the public domain on שבת Shabbos is
a prohibition that is related to carrying and I
want to show you the גמרא Gemara because the גמרא Gemara is
basically based
on the logic
of the people that
were part of the generation and specifically of רבינו הקדוש. Rabbeinu Hakadosh.
So it's on
דף פ Daf Pey in the גמרא Gemara and the גמרא Gemara
asks the following question: מנין למוציא כגרוגרת בשבת שהוא חייב? Minyan Lemotzi
Kegrogeret Beshabbos Shehu Chayav? Where do we know that
if a person carries an amount of food equal
to the size of
a dried fig on שבת Shabbos that he is חייב? chayav? And
the answer that the גמרא Gemara gives is: שכן משא בני
קהת. Sheken Massa Bnei Kehat. Just like the carrying of the
sons of קהת Kehat in the משכן. Mishkan. And the גמרא Gemara
then asks: ומשא בני קהת מנלן? Umassa Bnei Kehat Menalan? Where do
we know about
the carrying of the sons of קהת? Kehat? And the גמרא Gemara
answers:
דכתיב וכמקדש חנייתו. Dechtiv Uchemikdash Chaniato. As the holiness is its resting
place. And the גמרא Gemara goes on to explain that
since they carried the parts of the משכן Mishkan on their shoulders,
that is
the source for the definition of carrying. But then the גמרא Gemara
asks an interesting question: ואימא ביד? Ve'eima Beyad? Maybe it has
to be in the hand? Why does it have to be on
the shoulder? אמר רבא אמר קרא על הכתף ישאו. Amar Rava Amar
Kra Al Hakatef Yisau. The פסוק pasuk says they
carried it on the shoulder. Now what's fascinating here is that the
גמרא Gemara is trying to
find a source for something that we almost take for
granted. We assume that carrying is forbidden. But
the גמרא Gemara is looking for the specific שיעור, shiur, the specific
amount of
a גרוגרת. grogeret. The גמרא Gemara asks: והא משא בני קהת
טובא הוה? Veha Massa Bnei Kehat Tuva Hava? But the burden of
the sons of קהת Kehat was much more than
a fig! It was the ארון, Aron, it was the שלחן, Shulchan,
it was the מנורה. Menorah. Those things are much bigger
than a גרוגרת. grogeret. So how does that prove the amount of
a dried fig? So the גמרא Gemara answers: גמירי דכל מאי דחשיב
חשיב. Gemiri Dechol Mai Dechashiv Chashiv. We
have a tradition that whatever is significant is significant. So
the idea is that the מלאכת הוצאה, Melechet Hotzaah, the labor of
carrying, is not just about moving an
object, it's about the significance of the object. And
the גמרא Gemara uses the משכן Mishkan as the archetype for what
is significant. If it
was significant in the משכן, Mishkan, it's significant for us on שבת.
Shabbos. There is a famous saying: סוף מעשה
במחשבה תחילה. Sof ma'aseh bemachshavah techilah. The end of the action starts
with a thought in the beginning. In the beginning, you have to
think it out. You have to have a
clear picture of what you want to achieve. If a person just
says, I'm going to be a צדיק, tzaddik, I'm going to be
a חסיד, chasid, and he doesn't know the rules and he doesn't
know the הלכות, halachot, he's going to fall. The חפץ
חיים Chofetz Chaim says in the introduction to the משנה ברורה Mishnah
Berurah that
if a person doesn't
learn the הלכות halachot of שבת, Shabbat, it's impossible, simply impossible, not
to transgress the laws of שבת. Shabbat. He's going to carry, he's
going to do מוקצה, muktzah, he's
going to do all kinds of things because he doesn't know. He
has good intentions. He wants to be שומר
שבת. shomer Shabbat. But he doesn't have the מחשבה. machshavah. He didn't
have the
thought. He didn't have the learning. And therefore, the מעשה, ma'aseh, the
action, is not going to
be a good מעשה. ma'aseh. He's going to fail. And this
is true in everything.
A person wants to be a בעל חסד.
ba'al chesed. He wants to do goodness. But
if he doesn't know the הלכות halachot of how to do חסד,
chesed, he might do more harm than good. He might give money
to the wrong people. He might do things that are actually
against the תורה. Torah. So the first step in everything
is מחשבה. machshavah. Think it through. Learn the הלכות. halachot. Get a
clear picture of what the רבונו של עולם Ribono Shel Olam wants
from us. And then, once you have that מחשבה, machshavah, then you
can
go and do the מעשה. ma'aseh. The Ran ר"ן Ran asks, the
Rosh רא"ש Rosh says it's a טענת ברי. taanat bari. And since
it's
a טענת ברי taanat bari and the other guy is a שמא,
shema, so ברי ושמא ברי עדיף. bari veshema bari adif. The Ran
ר"ן Ran says it's not a טענת ברי. taanat bari. Why?
Because he doesn't know for sure. He says
I didn't get it, but maybe the שליח shaliach gave it to
his wife or someone else in the house. So it's not a
ברי, bari, it's a שמא. shema. Since it's
a שמא, shema, then it's שמא ושמא, shema veshema, and המוציא מחבירו
עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav haraaya. The גמרא Gemara in בבא בתרא
Bava Batra on דף ח daf Ches discusses the laws of צדקה.
tzedakah. It says that every city must have a קופה kuppah
and a תמחוי. tamchui. What is the difference between the two? The
קופה kuppah was
a fund where they collected money every Friday from the residents of
the city. This money was
then distributed to the poor of the city, the עניי העיר, aniyei
ha'ir, so they would have
enough for שבת Shabbos and the rest of the week. On the
other hand, the תמחוי tamchui was
a food collection. They would go around every day
and collect food for anyone who was hungry.
Even an עני ani passing through the city could eat from the
תמחוי. tamchui. The
גבאים gabbaim who collected the קופה kuppah had to be at least
two people so that there would be no
suspicion of theft. However, when it came to distributing the money, it
required three people. This is because determining how much each person needs
is a form of דין, din, a judgment, and
we need
a בית דין beis din of three to make that decision.
For the תמחוי, tamchui, both the collection and the distribution were done
by
three people because the food was distributed on the same day it
was collected. The שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch writes that today we
don't have exactly the same system of קופה kuppah and תמחוי tamchui
as they had in the times
of the גמרא, Gemara, but the concept of communal responsibility for the
poor remains a מחויבות, mechuyavut, an obligation. Every community has
a מנהג minhag of how they collect and distribute their
צדקה tzedakah funds. Any resident who stays in a city for thirty
days is already obligated to contribute to the קופה. kuppah. If he
stays for three months, he contributes to the תמחוי. tamchui. After six
months, he contributes to the clothing fund, and after nine months,
he contributes to the burial fund, the חברה קדישא.
chevra
kadisha.
This shows that the longer a person is part of a קהילה,
kehillah, the more responsibilities he
takes on for the welfare of others. Well. Good. How are you?
Yeah. What? What list? I was. Yeah, well, it was
a very weird list of names they decided to
mention explicitly in the article, but anyway, but if you look at
the list, yeah. I was
linked to in the article. Oh, I didn't see that it was
Jewish Week's article, I saw the article somewhere
else. I saw the article somewhere else, I don't remember, I didn't.
What? I was assuming. Well, it wasn't limited
to that, but I'm guessing probably הדסה Hadassah's the primary. No, I
don't know if anybody like follow is
a recent news item, right? Like I didn't see
it in this week's printed Jewish Week, was it? Right. Right. Yeah,
yeah, I mean I'm getting a lot of stuff, we're about to
launch a new website that is, that's gonna have a lot of
stuff, gonna be very, very good. Yeah. Yeah, and then did you
want to, what were you, you've been asking
something about שבת? Shabbos? So, all right let me
check with דבורה Dvora again, I forgot to ask
her. Okay. Right. All right I'll ask דבורה,
Dvora, it should be fine but I'll ask
her. Because the תורה Torah demands that you treat him with the
same level of comfort that you have. If you have one pillow,
you give it to him. If you have one cup of wine,
you give it to him. This teaches us
a tremendous amount about the human dignity that the תורה Torah requires
for every single person, even
a person who is in a state of servitude. Yeah, and then,
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah that weekend. Oh, wait a minute.
That might be hard, because that might be
the weekend he's leaving to Israel. I have to, let me, I'll
check with דבורה. Devorah. I have to, it might be a very,
like, you know, it might be tight. He's
leaving to Israel right around then. So actually
might be a little complicated. So let me check it with דבורה.
Devorah. Okay. Yeah, sure. Speak to her. Right,
right. Alright, see you then. Okay, very good.
The הדרן Hadran that we say, it starts with
high priority for every person. The הדרן Hadran for the מסכת Masechet
we learn. הדרן עלך, Hadran alach, we should return to you. And
then it continues, we thank ה' Hashem for the fact that we
sit in the בית המדרש. Beit HaMidrash. מודה אני לפניך ה' אלוהינו
ואלוהי אבותינו ששמת חלקי מיושבי בית המדרש. Modeh ani lifanecha Hashem Elokeinu
v'Elokei avoteinu she'samta chelki mi'yoshvei Beit HaMidrash. I thank
you that you put my portion among those
who sit in the study hall. And
I wasn't put in the portion of those who sit on the
street corner. Now, this sounds very elitist. What's going on here? We
are better than them? Is it some sort
of exclusive club? Let's read further and see
if we can find some answers. אנחנו משכימים
והם משכימים. Anachnu mashkimim v'heim mashkimim. We wake up early and they
wake up early. אנחנו משכימים לדברי תורה והם
משכימים לדברים בטלים. Anachnu mashkimim l'divrei Torah v'heim mashkimim l'dvarim bateilim. We
wake up for words of Torah, and they
wake up for useless things. אנחנו עמלים והם
עמלים. Anachnu ameilim v'heim ameilim. We work hard and they work hard.
אנחנו עמלים ומקבלים שכר והם עמלים ואינם מקבלים
שכר. Anachnu ameilim u'mekablim sachar v'heim ameilim v'einam mekablim sachar. Wait a
second. This doesn't seem right. People who work in the street, whether
they're merchants or bankers or doctors, don't they get paid for their
work? Of course they do. So what does it mean they don't
get שכר, sachar, they don't get reward? The difference lies in the
nature of the reward. In the world of the
street, you're paid for the outcome. A builder gets paid for the
house he built. If he works for ten years and there's no
house, he doesn't get paid. But in the world
of תורה, Torah, in the world of רוחניות, ruchniyut, spirituality, we are
paid for the effort. לפום
צערא אגרא. L'fum tza'ara agra. According to the pain is the reward.
Even if
you don't finish the מסכת, Masechet, even if
you don't understand the סוגיא, sugya, the fact
that you
tried,
the
fact that you labored, that itself is the reward. That's why we
say we are משכימים mashkimim
and we receive שכר. sachar. The reward is for the עמל, amal,
for
the toil itself. This is a
profound shift
in perspective. It's not about
the bottom line. It's about the
process. It's about
the journey. And that's why we can say
with
confidence that our portion is different. Our focus
is
on
growth through effort, not just achievement of results. So when we say
the הדרן, Hadran, let's keep that in mind. It's a celebration of
the work
we
put in, regardless of the output. The תורה Torah becomes part
of us because of the sweat we poured into it. The
provided audio consists entirely of static noise and does not contain any
discernible speech or
words to transcribe. So we see שמה מתנה,
shemah
matanah, it is indeed considered a
gift. The גמרא Gemara asks, is this not obvious?
Why do I need a ברייתא braisa to tell me that if
he did not return it, לא יצא, lo yatza, he did not
fulfill his obligation? If the condition was not met, then the gift
is nullified. The גמרא Gemara explains that it is needed for a
case where the אתרוג esrog was stolen or lost. Even though it
was
an אונס, oness, since he did not return it, the condition was
not fulfilled and it is not a gift. איתיביה, Aisiveh,
he raised an objection
to him from a משנה Mishna in מסכת קידושין. Masechet Kiddushin. If
a man says הרי את מקודשת לי, harei at mekudeshes li, be
betrothed to me with this object, על מנת
שתחזירהו לי, al menas shetachzirehu li, on condition that you return it
to me, if she returns it, she is
מקודשת. mekudeshes.
If she does not return it, she is
not מקודשת. mekudeshes. This proves again that מתנה על
מנת להחזיר matanah al menas lehachzir שמה מתנה, shemah matanah, it is
considered a gift. The גמרא Gemara asks, why do
we need both cases? Why do we need
the case of אתרוג esrog and the case of קידושין? kiddushin? We
need them both, because if we only had the case of אתרוג,
esrog, I might say it works there because it is a מצוה
mitzvah and the person gives the gift
wholeheartedly.
But by
קידושין, kiddushin,
where he
might be
more stingy, I would say it is not a gift. And if
we only had the case of קידושין, kiddushin, I would say it
works there because a woman is willing to
accept any benefit to
be married,
but by אתרוג, esrog, maybe not. Therefore, both are
necessary. The גמרא Gemara also says that if he
says return
it to me, and he dies, she cannot
return it
to the יורשים yorshim because he specifically said לי, li, to me.
If he did not say לי, li, she could return it to
the יורשים yorshim and the gift would be valid. We see
from here how
important the לשון lashon of the condition is in הלכה.
halacha. Hello. Good
morning. העש? Hesch? No,
no, no, did you wait for
me? I mean, I'm not as early a riser as you, but,
you know, what I get done before most people are up? It's
like the Marines. I've already given the דף, Daf, I've written the
הלכה, Halacha, anyway, what can I do for you?
Sure. Yeah. Aha, well,
let me tell you the number I have. By the way, since
I've already, I've done you another favor. Haha.
I sent somebody your
way, a woman who's having a
lot of bleeding at intercourse, she's an over
the first שאלה, sheila, she's just married recently, and like, and she's
gone to
a gynecologist, and the gynecologist said everything looks normal. So it's like,
anyway, so just expect a call like that.
The one number I have is 347-792-9365. Is that the one you
have? Ah, ah, ah, oh, I see. Restricted,
you didn't see the incoming number. 347-792-9365. Sure, be well. Sure, good
night. And the גמרא Gemara answers, that's only during one's lifetime, but
before one is נפטר, niftar, one is allowed
to give more. But the question is,
why did he give specifically half? Why half of his money? The
answer is, because there's a limit to how much a person can
give even before he is נפטר. niftar. There is
an opinion that says even a שכיב מרע,
shchiv meira, a person who is
on his deathbed, shouldn't give away all his
money. He should leave some for his יורשים. yorshim. And the amount
that's usually mentioned is up to half. That's why מר עוקבא Mar
Ukva gave specifically half of his money. He wanted to give as
much as possible, but he
also had to follow the
הלכה halacha of not leaving his heirs with nothing. So
he gave exactly half. This shows us the balance a person has
to have. Even when
doing a great מצוה mitzvah like צדקה, tzedakah, one has to follow
the rules of the תורה. Torah. You can't just do whatever you
want. There's
a גדר, geder, there's a limit, and we have to follow the
instructions of our חכמים. Chachamim. We are on דף ט"ו *Daf Tes
Vav* in מסכת masechet. יבמות *Masechet Yevamos*. The גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is currently dealing with the relationship between בית Bayit שמאי
Shammai *Beis Shammai* and בית הלל Hallel? *Beis Hillel*. We know that
there
was a major מחלוקת machloket *machloket* regarding the case of צרות *tzaros*.
According to בית שמאי Shammai *Beis Shammai*, the צרה *tzarah*
is permitted to the יבם *yavam*, whereas according to בית הלל Hallel
*Beis Hillel*, she is forbidden as a case of ערווה *erva*. This
is
a significant issue because it could lead to questions of ממזרות *mamzerus*.
However, the משנה mishnah *mishnah* teaches us that לא lo נמנעו *lo
nimneu*, they did not refrain from marrying into
each other's families. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* asks: תא
שמע Shema *Ta Shama*, come and hear. We
have a ברייתא braisa *braita* that says they behaved with אמת
Emes. *emes* and שלום Shalom *shalom*. They were not
מונע *moneh* their daughters from marrying because they
were מודע *moda*, they would inform each other
of any potential status issues. This shows that
their מחלוקת machloket *machloket* was truly לשם שמים *l'shem
shamayim*, for the sake of heaven. This is a גוואלדיקע *gevaldige* יסוד
Yesod *yesod* for us today. Even when we have a difference in
הלכה halacha. *halacha*, we must maintain אהבה *ahava* and רעות *re'us* within
the בית מדרש Midrash, *beis midrash* and across all of כלל ישראל
Klal Yisrael *Klal Yisrael*. We see that they followed the path of
האמת והשלום אהבו *ha'emes
ve'hashalom ahavu*. This is the main נקודה *nekudah* of the סוגיא sugya
*sugya* we
are learning on the דף *daf*. So once again, we are dealing
with the שבע מצות בני נח as they appear in the
תורה Torah and in the words of the נביאים. Neviim. Now let's
continue with today's
topic, which is the מצוה Mitzvah of עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. Okay,
are we ready to start? Ready. So today
I thought we would
start a new מסכת. We're going to start מסכת
ברכות. Masechet Berachot. The first משנה Mishnah in the first פרק perek
starts off asking about the time for קריאת שמע. Kriyat Shema. מאימתי
קורין את שמע בערבית? Me'ematai korin et shema be'arvit? From when do
we
recite the שמע Shema? in the evening? משעה שהכהנים נכנסים לאכול בתרומתן.
Mishe'ah shehakohanim nichnasim le'echol b'terumatan. From the time that the כהנים kohanim
enter to eat their תרומה. terumah. עד
סוף האשמורה הראשונה. Ad sof ha'ashmurah harishonah. Until the end of the
first watch. This is the דברי רבי
אליעזר. divrei Rabbi Eliezer. These are the words of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi
Eliezer. וחכמים אומרים, Vachachamim omrim, and the חכמים chachamim say, עד חצות,
ad chatzot, until midnight. רבן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Gamliel omer, רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel says, עד שיעלה
עמוד השחר, ad she'ya'aleh amud hashachar, until the break of dawn. The
גמרא Gemara begins on דף ב עמוד א. daf bet amud alef.
And the first thing it asks is: תנא היכא קאי דקתני
מאימתי? Tanna heicha kai d'ka'tani me'ematai? Where does the תנא tanna stand
that he asks from when? In other words,
why did he choose to start here? Why
is he starting with the evening שמע? Shema And why didn't he
start by saying we have an obligation to say it? It answers:
תנא אקרא קאי. Tanna akra kai. The תנא tanna is basing himself
on
a פסוק. pasuk. דכתיב בשכבך ובקומך. Dechtiv beshochbecha uvkumecha. As it is
written, when you lie down and when you
rise up. הכי קתני. Hechi ka'tani. This is what the תנא tanna
is teaching. זמן קריאת שמע דשכיבה מאימתי? Zman kriyat shema d'shchivah me'ematai?
When is the time
for the recitation of the שמע Shema. of lying
down? And the answer is משעה שהכהנים נכנסים לאכול
בתרומתן. Mishe'ah shehakohanim nichnasim le'echol b'terumatan. From the time the כהנים kohanim
enter to eat their תרומה. terumah. And we know that the day
follows the
night based on the description of creation, ויהי ערב ויהי בקר יום
אחד. Vayehi erev vayehi voker yom echad. And there was evening and
there was morning, one day. Therefore, the תנא
tanna starts with the evening. It teaches us
something extra on the side, a way to learn additional הלכה. halacha.
It's a way for the תנא tanna to remind us about the
purity of the כהנים. kohanim. And it's really the idea of
a connection that's much deeper than just how I
feel in the moment. Because if I only do something for you
when I feel like it, then the relationship is only as strong
as my feelings. But if I
have a מצווה, Mitzvah, an obligation, then the relationship is built
on something eternal. Now, let's look at the specific examples the גמרא
Gemara gives. The גמרא Gemara says that
a husband is obligated in three things: שאר, She'er, which is food;
כסות, Kesut, which is clothing; and עונה, Onah, which is
often translated as intimacy or responsiveness. These are
the three pillars of what a husband must provide for his wife.
And it's interesting because these aren't just physical things. They represent emotional
needs as well. Food is about sustenance and care. Clothing
is about dignity and protection. And עונה Onah is
about that deep, soulful connection and responsiveness to
one another. On the other side, the גמרא Gemara, talks about the
wife's role, and it uses the term מעשי
ידיה, Ma'asei Yadeiha, which means the work of her hands. But again,
this isn't about being a servant. It's about
her contribution to the home, her partnership in building
a life together. The גמרא Gemara also discusses something called
שלום בית, Shalom Bayit, which we usually translate as peace in the
home. But שלום Shalom, comes from the word שלם, Shalem, which means
whole or complete. So שלום בית Shalom Bayit isn't just about not
fighting; it's about making the home
a complete and holy place. The רמב״ם, Rambam, in הלכות אישות, Hilchot
Ishut, explains that a husband should love his wife like himself and
honor her more than himself. And a wife
should honor her husband and see him as a partner in building
their shared destiny. This is the blueprint
for a relationship that lasts. It's not built on the shifting sands
of emotion, but on the solid rock of תורה Torah and מצוות.
Mitzvot. When we follow this path, we're
not just two people living together; we're creating
a שכינה, Shechinah, a divine presence that dwells between us. But the
key is to remember that the effort is just the vessel, it's
not the cause. The cause is always השם. Hashem. And that brings
us to the next point, which is the
level of בטחון. Bitachon. The חובות הלבבות Chovos HaLevavos explains that
there are different levels of trust. The highest level is when a
person feels
like a child
in the hands of their mother. The
child doesn't worry about where their next meal
is coming from, they don't worry about whether
they have clothes to wear. They just trust
that their parents will take care of everything. That is the essence
of בטחון. Bitachon. It's a sense of total surrender to the רצון
השם. Ratzon Hashem. Now, many people struggle with this because we live
in a world that values independence and taking control. We are taught
from a young age that if we want something, we have to
go out and get it. And while השתדלות
Hishtadlus is necessary, we can't let it become
our primary focus. The moment we think that
our success is solely a result of our
own efforts, we have lost our בטחון. Bitachon. We
have to remember the words of the גמרא, Gemara which says that
everything is in the hands of heaven except for the fear of
heaven. הכל בידי שמים חוץ מיראת שמים. Hakol Biyedei Shamayim Chutz Miyiras
Shamayim. Our job is to
do our part, the השתדלות, Hishtadlus, but to leave the results to
הקדוש ברוך הוא. Hakadosh Baruch Hu. This is
a lifelong work. It's not something that happens overnight.
It requires constant reinforcement through learning תורה Torah and
through תפילה. Tefillah. When we דאוון, Daven, we are acknowledging
that we are dependent on השם Hashem for everything.
We ask for health, we ask for פרנסה,
Parnassah, we ask for wisdom. And in doing so, we are strengthening
our מדת הבטחון. Middas HaBitachon. It's about living with the constant awareness
that we are never alone. No matter how difficult the situation may
seem, there is a בורא עולם Borei Olam who is guiding us.
And even if we don't understand why things are happening the way
they are, we can still have שלום, peace, knowing that it's all
for the best. כל דעביד
רחמנא לטב עביד, Kol Deavid Rachmana Letav Avid, whatever the Merciful One
does, He does for the good. The גמרא Gemara then mentions an
incident
where a certain person was walking in the public domain and he
tripped over a jug and broke it. רב
פפא Rav Papa said that even if the person who placed the
jug was in the process of moving it, the one who broke
it would still be פטור. patur. Wait, why? If
he's moving it, isn't he
trying to clear the path? רב פפא Rav Papa explains that since
the public domain is meant for walking, people don't expect obstacles. It's
like what we saw before: לפי שאין דרכן
של בני אדם להסתכל בדרכים. Lefi she-ein darkan shel bnei adam lehistakel
badrachim. There's
another case in the משנה Mishnah about a person who fell into
a pit. If someone digs
a בור bor in a public place and someone else falls into
it, the one who dug the pit is
liable. But what if the person who
fell was looking at the birds or something? Does that change things?
The גמרא Gemara
discusses whether negligence
on the part of the one who fell matters. If the obstacle
was clearly visible, should they have seen it? רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
says that even if it's broad daylight, people
are not necessarily looking down.
Interesting. So it's about the expectation of a clear path. Exactly. The
responsibility stays with the person who created
the hazard in the רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. Okay, let's look at
the next part where it says: נתקלה בקרקע. Nitkelah bakkarka. Wait, let
me find that. Ah, okay. If she tripped
on the ground
and then broke the jug. The גמרא Gemara is distinguishing between tripping
on the object itself versus tripping on the ground
and then hitting the object. Is the person
still פטור patur then? Yes, the principle
remains the same. The person shouldn't have put the
object there in the first place. Let's move on to the next
section about damages caused by one's property, like a שור, shor, an
ox. We've touched on this before, right? The
distinction between תם tam and מועד. muad. Yes, an ox
that is תם tam pays only half damages, חצי
נזק, chatzi nezek, while a מועד muad pays full damages, נזק שלם.
nezek shalem. And where does this apply? It applies in various settings,
but the rules change depending on whether it's the owner's property or
the רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. This is
all part of the laws of נזיקין. Nezikin. This means that we
need to have the right יראת שמים yirat shamayim before we begin
our תפילה. tefillah. The reason for this is because when
we stand before the רבונו של עולם, Ribbono Shel Olam, we must
recognize who we are speaking to. It is
not just a matter of saying words; it
is a matter of the heart. The משנה Mishnah explains that the
חסידים הראשונים Chassidim HaRishonim would wait an entire hour before they would
start to דאוון. daven. Why did they do this?
To settle their minds and focus their hearts
towards their אבינו שבשמים. Avinu Shebashamayim. This preparation is essential
for a meaningful עבודה שבלב. avodah shebalev. When a person rushes into
their prayers without any prior thought, it is hard to achieve the
level of כוונה kavanah that is required. We see this idea throughout
the הלכה. halacha For example, there are certain things one should avoid
doing right before תפילת מנחה Tefillat Mincha or תפילת שחרית Tefillat Shacharit
to ensure that they do not get distracted. The
goal is always the same: to arrive at the moment of prayer
with
a clear head and a heart full of דבקות. dveikut. This is
not just for the pious individuals; it
is a
guide for every single יהודי. Yid. We all have
the capacity to connect, but we need to
put in the effort of הכנה. hachanah. By taking even just
a few moments to contemplate the greatness of the בורא עולם, Borei
Olam, we can transform our entire experience from a
routine task into a powerful spiritual encounter. to
rest upon. Today we are going to talk
about a very important topic, which is the concept of a משכן.
Mishkan. The Torah tells us about the construction of
the משכן Mishkan in great detail. Why does the Torah spend so
much time on the details of the משכן? Mishkan? The
רמב"ן Ramban explains that the purpose of the משכן
Mishkan
was to continue the experience of מעמד הר סיני. Maamad Har Sinai.
At הר סיני, Har Sinai, the שכינה Shechinah rested upon the mountain.
Through the משכן, Mishkan, the שכינה Shechinah would rest among the Jewish
people. But there is
a very deep lesson here. The גמרא gemara says in מסכת ברכות
Masechet Brachot that בצלאל Bezalel knew how to combine the letters with
which heaven and earth were created. What
does
this mean? It means that the משכן Mishkan was not just a
physical building. It
was a microcosm of the world. Every part of the משכן Mishkan
corresponded to
a different part of the universe. And just as הקדוש ברוך הוא
Hakadosh Baruch Hu created the world with a specific
order, a specific חכמה, chochma, so too the משכן Mishkan had to
be built with a specific order. This brings
us back to what we said before about
a סדר. seder. Without a סדר, seder, there is no
place for the שכינה Shechinah to rest. The משכן Mishkan is called
a משכן Mishkan because
it's a place where the שכינה Shechinah dwells, שוכן. shochen. If we
want to build
a משכן Mishkan in our own lives, we need to create a
structure. We need to have
a סדר seder in our learning, a סדר seder in our דאוונען,
davening,
a סדר seder in our overall behavior. When a person has a
סדר, seder, he becomes a כלי kli for the ברכה bracha of
הקדוש ברוך הוא. Hakadosh Baruch Hu. The פסוק pasuk says, ועשו לי
מקדש ושכנתי בתוכם. Ve'asu li mikdash v'shachanti b'tocham. It doesn't say ושכנתי
בתוכו, v'shachanti b'tocho, in it, but
rather בתוכם, b'tocham, in them. Every single one of us has the
ability to
become a משכן. Mishkan. Every single one
of us can bring the שכינה Shechinah into our lives. But it
requires effort. It requires preparation. Just like
the Jews in the מדבר midbar had to gather all the materials
for the משכן. Mishkan. They brought gold, silver, and copper. They brought
תכלת, techelet, ארגמן, argaman, and תולעת שני. tola'at shani. They gave from
their hearts. כל איש אשר ידבנו לבו. kol ish asher yidvenu libo.
This is the
key. It's about the heart. But the heart needs to be directed
by
a סדר. seder. When we take our passion and we
channel it through a structured way of life, that is when we
truly succeed. That is when we see the סייעתא דשמיא siyaata d'shmaya
in everything we do. Ready? Okay עכשיו Achshav מתחילה Matchila הצפירה Hatzfira
one minute. Done, that's it זהו.
Zehu.
We are in פרשת צו. Parshas Tzav. And the connection between פרשת
צו Parshas Tzav and the upcoming holiday of פסח. Pesach. One of
the key קרבנות Korbanos
we learn about in the פרשה Parsha is the קרבן תודה, Korban
Todah, which as the name implies is brought when someone has something
to thank ה' Hashem for.
The גמרא gemara in ברכות Berachos says there are four categories: somebody
who went through the sea, the
desert, was in jail, or was sick. And they bring this
קרבן Korban to acknowledge the חסד chesed of ה'. Hashem. What's fascinating
about this קרבן Korban is that it has
a lot of bread, לחם, lechem, forty loaves of bread. And the
timeframe to eat it is
very limited, until the morning. And the נצי"ב Netziv asks, why so
much bread in such
a short time? He explains that the תורה Torah wanted to force
the person to make
a party, to invite friends and family, so that
while they are eating, he will tell over the story of the
miracle that happened to
him. This is the concept of פרסומי ניסא. pirsumei nisa. And this
is the same idea as the
סדר Seder night. We have the מצוה mitzvah of והגדת לבנך. v'higadta
l'vincha. We sit around the table
and we tell the story of יציאת מצרים. Yetzias Mitzrayim. And just
like the קרבן תודה Korban Todah was meant
to be shared, the פסח Pesach is
meant to be shared as well. In the הגדה Haggadah we say
כל דכפין ייתי וייכל, kol d'ichfin yeisei v'yeichol, let all who are
hungry come and eat.
It's about sharing the gratitude and sharing the story. May we
all merit to see the גאולה geulah and bring the קרבן פסח
Korban Pesach this year in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. The גמרא Gemara in
גיטין gittin דף לב daf lamed beis discusses a מחלוקת machlokes between
רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. רב Rav says that if a
person appoints a שליח shaliach to give
a גט get to his wife, he must do it in front
of two witnesses. Why? Because we are worried that the husband might
later cancel the גט, get, a process called ביטול הגט. bitul ha'get.
If there are
no witnesses to the appointment, it is easier for him to deny
the whole thing. שמואל, Shmuel, however, argues that you do
not need witnesses for the
appointment of a שליח. shaliach. Why? Because of the principle שליחו של
אדם כמותו, shlucho shel adam k'moto, the
agent stands in the place of the principal. Just as the principal
does not need witnesses to say he wants
to do something, the agent does not need witnesses to be empowered.
The גמרא Gemara asks how
can שמואל Shmuel ignore the concern of ביטול? bitul? The answer is
that we follow the חזקה chazakah
that a שליח shaliach does his mission, שליח עושה שליחותו.
shaliach oseh shlichuto. We also discuss the issue of a פרוזבול. pruzbul.
Can a person appoint a שליח shaliach to hand
over his debts to the בית דין? beit din? Again, we have
a similar debate. Some say it must be done in front of
the בית דין beit din itself, while others say
a שליח shaliach is sufficient. This teaches us the power of שליחות
shlichut in הלכה halacha and how it functions as
a legal extension of the individual. Whether it is for גטין gittin
or for financial matters like שמיטה, shmita, the role of the
שליח shaliach is central to the functioning of the legal system. But
for שחרית Shacharis and מנחה, Mincha, you must go back.
What
if a person forgot in שחרית Shacharis and then they already
said הלל? Hallel, Does the הלל Hillel count as a mention of
the day so they don't have to repeat שחרית? Shacharis? The משנה
ברורה Mishnah Berurah says no. Even if you said הלל,
Hillel and even if you said מוסף, Musaf, you
still have to
repeat שחרית Shacharis because the mention of the day needs to be
in its correct place in the תפילה,
tefillah,
which is in רצה. Retzei. Since it was missing from the שמונה
עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, the תפילה tefillah is not complete and you have
to repeat it.
The next משנה Mishnah says: the House of שמאי say, they don't
do
something, we
should say the Hebrew first. בית שמאי אומרים אין שורפין בשר שנטמא
בוולד הטומאה עם בשר שנטמא באב הטומאה. Beit Shammai omerim ein sorfin
basar she-nitma be-velad ha-tum'ah im basar she-nitma be-av ha-tum'ah. The House of
שמאי say we don't burn meat that became
impure with a child of impurity, which is a lower level, with
meat that became impure through a father of impurity, which
is a higher level. והלל
אומרים שורפין. Ve-Hillel omerim sorfin. The House of הלל hallel, say we
do burn them together. Even though by putting
them together, we're technically making the lower level
one a bit more impure by touching it to the
higher level one, הלל hallel says since they're both
going to be burned anyway, it doesn't matter.
And then the משנה Mishnah continues with the opinion of רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. אמר רבי מאיר מדבריהם למדנו ששורפין תרומה טהורה עם הטמאה
בפסח. Amar Rabbi Meir midivreihem lamadnu she-sorfin terumah tehorah im ha-tmeiah be-Pesach.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said: from their words we learned that we
burn pure תרומה terumah with impure תרומה terumah on Passover. Which is
a big jump because here we're actually taking
something pure and making it impure. But he
says because we're destroying it anyway, we can
do it together. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose answers him: אמר
רבי יוסי אינה היא המידה. Amar Rabbi Yose einah hi ha-midah. רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose said: this is not a proper comparison. And the
גמרא Gemara will go into the details of the argument. The גמרא
Gemara is located on page דף מ"ו עמוד א'. Daf Mem Vav
Amud Aleph. That's 46a. It's towards the middle of the page. The
גמרא Gemara says איתמר, Itmar, it was stated המוכר ספינה, Hamocheir sefina,
one who sells a ship. מכר את העבירה, Machar et ha'avira, he
sold the—I believe it's the mast. רב Rav אמר, amar, רב Rav
says עבירה שמיה, avira shemiya, ושמואל u'Shmuel אמר, amar, שמואל Shmuel says
לא שמיה עבירה. lo shemiya avira, Rav says that the act of
passing or the equipment used for it is considered an integral
part of the vessel, whereas Shmuel says it is not.
The גמרא Gemara asks, מאי mai עבירה? avira What exactly is
this עבירה? avira. אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Pappa, רב פפא Rav
Pappa says, דמשיכא, d'mashicha, it refers to the
ropes used for pulling the ship. The debate
centers on whether the term ספינה sefina is broad enough to include
these accessories by default. רב Rav holds עבירה avira? שמיה,
shemiya, that it is indeed called part of the ship's operation and
thus included in the sale. שמואל Shmuel argues לא שמיה shemiya עבירה,
avira? that these are separate entities. The גמרא
Gemara then attempts to bring support from a
ברייתא which discusses how one acquires
a ship and whether components like the anchor, the
sails, or the small boats are part of the transaction. This leads
into
a larger discussion of קניינים kinyanim and the specific acts required to
take ownership of large items in different domains such as the רשות
הרבים reshus harabbim or
a private alleyway. We see that the definition of what constitutes a
vessel versus its accessories is
crucial for establishing the parameters of the הלכה halacha in business dealings.
But if we want to learn it through
a פסוק, pasuk, through
a גזרה שוה, gezerah shavah, then we learn it through the
גזרה שוה. gezerah shavah. We then discover that maybe the principle of
עשה דוחה לא תעשה aseh docheh lo taaseh is not as all-encompassing
as we thought and maybe it only applies to specific cases. The
גמרא Gemara then asks, how do we know that
specifically by ציצית tzitzit we should have the rule of עשה דוחה
לא תעשה? aseh docheh lo taaseh? Maybe it's because there's a certain
unique characteristic to ציצית, tzitzit, which is the תכלת? techelet? So the
גמרא Gemara then says, no, because we have
a פסוק pasuk that says צמר ופשתים, tzemer upishtim, and right next
to it it says גדילים תעשה לך, gedilim ta'aseh lach, which
means you should make fringes. This סמיכות, smichut, this
juxtaposition, teaches us that even when it's שעטנז
shaatnez you can still wear the ציצית. tzitzit. But then the גמרא
Gemara asks, wait a second, that only works if the בגד beged
itself is made out of either צמר tzemer or פשתים. pishtim. What
if the בגד beged is made out of something else, like silk
or something? Then you're still not allowed to
wear שעטנז. shaatnez. So we need another source to
teach us that. And the גמרא
Gemara goes through various sources, including the word צמר
tzemer
and פשתים pishtim in the context of נגעים nega'im to try to
broaden the definition of what constitutes
a בגד. beged. Ultimately we come to the conclusion that while the
general rule of עשה דוחה לא תעשה aseh docheh lo taaseh might
apply, the specific case of ציצית tzitzit and שעטנז shaatnez is learned
through this סמיכות smichut of the
פסוקים. pesukim. And this is the whole idea of the עבודה Avodah
of a person, to take the רצון Ratzon which starts off as
an external thing,
as a חיצוניות, Chitzoniyut, and through the use of his שכל
Sechel to make it into a פנימיות, Pnimiyut, to
make it into his own inner will. Now
let's look at the difference between אמונה Emunah and שכל. Sechel. We
know that אמונה Emunah is higher than שכל. Sechel. But if אמונה
Emunah is higher than שכל, Sechel, why do we need שכל Sechel
at all? Why shouldn't a person just live
with אמונה? Emunah? The answer is that אמונה Emunah is
like רצון. Ratzon. It's a מקיף. Makif. It's something which is above
the person. And because it's above the person, it doesn't necessarily permeate
the person's entire being. A person can have אמונה Emunah and yet
his emotions and his actions can be completely
contrary to that אמונה.
Emunah.
This is what the גמרא Gemara says, גנבא אפום מחתרתא רחמנא קריא.
Ganva apum machtarta Rachmana karya. A thief, at the very moment he
is breaking into
a house to steal, calls out to the אייבערשטער Eibershter to help
him. Now, does he have אמונה? Emunah? Yes, he's davening to the
אייבערשטער. Eibershter. But his אמונה Emunah is
a מקיף. Makif. It's something which is outside of him. It hasn't
yet permeated his שכל Sechel and his מדות Middot to
the point where it would stop him
from stealing. So the point of שכל, Sechel, and specifically the עבודה
Avodah of
חסידות, Chassidut, which is the internalizing of the אלקות Elokut through שכל,
Sechel, is to take that אמונה Emunah and to
bring it down into the שכל. Sechel. Because when something
is understood in שכל, Sechel, then it becomes פנימיות. Pnimiyut. It becomes
part of the person himself. And once it's part of the person
himself, then it can affect his מדות Middot and his actual behavior.
This is why we need both. We need
the אמונה Emunah because
that connects us to the עצמות, Atzmut, to something which is beyond
שכל. Sechel. But we need the שכל Sechel in order to make
that אמונה Emunah real
and lived in our daily lives. Without the שכל, Sechel, the אמונה
Emunah remains a מקיף, Makif, and a person can remain a גנבא
Ganva even while he is רחמנא קריא. Rachmana karya. This
teaches us that נחמה nechama is a gift from
הקדוש ברוך הוא. HaKadosh Baruch Hu. Without this גזירה, gezeira, a person
would never be able to overcome their grief
and continue with their life. It was a
unique trial for יעקב Yaakov to carry this pain
for twenty-two years as if it had just
happened. But the truth is, time doesn't heal. Time just passes. It
is the גזירה gezeira that does the work. When we say ניחום
אבלים, nichum aveilim, we are performing an act of חסד chesed that
mirrors the divine. We are saying to the person, I cannot take
away your pain, but I can stand with you in the place
where the המקום Hamakom will eventually bring that נחמה. nechama. And this
is
why we use the specific formula of המקום ינחם אתכם בתוך שאר
אבלי ציון וירושלים. Hamakom yenachem eschem b'soch sh'ar aveilei Tzion v'Yerushalayim. We
are acknowledging that the healing is supernatural.
It's not within the realm of the natural world for a person
to lose
a part of themselves and yet continue to breathe
and eat and eventually even smile again. That
is the גזירה. gezeira. That is the miracle of the human spirit
when it is touched by the divine. We see that יעקב Yaakov
eventually was reunited with יוסף Yosef and he was able to see
his grandchildren, but those twenty-two years were
a testament to the fact that without the גזירה, gezeira, the pain
remains
as fresh as the moment it began. May we all be זוכה
zocheh to see the ultimate נחמה nechama of ציון Tzion and
ירושלים Yerushalayim speedily in our days. Hello. Yes. Who is this? ראובן,
Reuvein, how are you? Somewhat. Same here. Aha,
handed notes to the article I wrote, you mean? Oh, really? Cool.
I am not sure I wrote it or some students wrote it
based on some classes, but either way. Oh,
could you send that to me? I do
not know if I, I do not know
if I have that. Okay. Great. Mhm. Yeah,
sure. Hold on one second. Just let me,
just give me two seconds and then I
will get back on the phone. It does not even take one
second. Okay, thanks. Hi, yes. So hi, so what is up? How
are you? Good, good, good. Okay. So yeah, so go ahead, tell
me what is, so you have specific questions or you want to
just do a walkthrough? The גמרא Gemara in מסכת בבא קמא Masechet
Bava Kamma דף כ״ז daf chaf zayin discusses the concept of עביד
איניש דינא לנפשיה. avid inish dina l'nafshei. Can a person take the
law into their own hands? The רמב״ם Rambam in הלכות סנהדרין Hilchot
Sanhedrin says that in a case of פסידא, psida, where there is
a loss, one may do so. This is also
brought in the שולחן ערוך. Shulchan Aruch. The question is, how far
does this principle go? If someone steals from you,
can you go into their house and take
it back? The גמרא Gemara says yes, provided you
don't cause unnecessary damage. Now, if we look at the סוגיא Sugya.
in בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, we see a similar discussion regarding השבת
אבידה. hashavat aveida. The person who finds the object has
a מצוה mitzvah to return it. But what if the owner has
already given up hope, which we call יאוש? yeush? If there is
יאוש שלא מדעת, yeush she'lo mada'at, meaning the owner doesn't know he
lost it yet, is it considered יאוש? yeush? This
is a major מחלוקת between אביי ורבא. Abaye v'Rava. אביי Abaye says
לא הוי יאוש, lo havei yeush, it's not considered giving up
hope. רבא Rava says הוי יאוש, havei yeush, it is considered
giving up hope. The הלכה halacha follows רבא Rava in most cases,
but here the גמרא Gemara concludes that the הלכה halacha is like
אביי. Abaye.
This is one of the cases of יעל קגם, Yael Kagam, where
the הלכה Halacha is according to אביי. Abaye. Moving on
to a different topic, the משנה Mishnah in מסכת ברכות Masechet Berachot
discusses the times for תפילה. tefillah. Until when can
one say קריאת שמע Kriyat Shema of the morning? רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says until the end of the first watch. But
the חכמים Chachamim say until חצות, chatzot, midnight, or rather
midday depending on the context of the specific תפילה. tefillah. Wait, for
שחרית, Shacharit, it's until the fourth hour according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda. And the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says until midday. If
a person misses the time for תפילה, tefillah, they can
do a תפילת תשלומים. tefillat tashlumin. For example, if you missed שחרית,
Shacharit, you pray מנחה Mincha twice. The first one
is for מנחה Mincha and the second is the תשלומים tashlumin for
שחרית. Shacharit. However, this only applies if the omission was בשוגג, b'shogeg,
by mistake, and not במזיד, b'meizid, on purpose. The
גמרא Gemara also discusses the importance of כונה, kavanah, intention, during prayer.
One should stand up to pray only out
of a sense of כובד ראש, koved rosh, seriousness. The חסידים הראשונים
Chasidim HaRishonim used to wait an hour before praying to prepare their
hearts. In the context of
שבת, Shabbat, we have the concept of ל״ט מלאכות, lamed tet melachot,
the thirty-nine categories of forbidden work. One of these is הוצאה
מרשות לרשות, hotza'ah me'reshut l'reshut, carrying from one domain to another.
Specifically from a רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid, a private domain,
to a רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, a public
domain. This is derived from the construction of
the משכן Mishkan in the desert. Whatever was done for the משכן
Mishkan is
considered a מלאכה melachah on שבת. Shabbat. We also have the concept
of מוקצה, muktzeh, objects that cannot be moved on שבת Shabbat because
they are set aside. There are different types of מוקצה, muktzeh, like
כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור,
kli she'melachto
l'isur, a tool used for
forbidden work. Understanding these rules is essential for
proper שבת Shabbat observance. In this week's פרשה, Parsha, פרשת
ואתחנן, Parshas Va'eschanan, we read the words of שמע ישראל. Shema Yisrael.
And there is a very interesting explanation brought down by the ספרים
הקדושים. Seforim HaKedoshim. Why is it that we say שמע ישראל ה'
אלקינו ה' אחד? Shema Yisrael Hashem Elokeinu Hashem Echad? And
they explain that the world is filled with things that distract us
from הקדוש ברוך הוא. HaKadosh Baruch Hu. The גשמיות Gashmius of the
world, the physical pleasures, they can sometimes blind us to the אמת.
emet. And that is why we cover our eyes when we say
שמע. Because we want
to block out the physical world and focus only on the רבונו
של עולם. Ribono Shel Olam. The גמרא Gemara, in ברכות Berachos tells
us that one should prolong the
word אחד Echad in order to establish the מלכות Malchus of ה'
Hashem in the four corners of the
world and in the heavens and the earth. This
is a very powerful יסוד yesod in our עבודת ה', Avodas Hashem,
to realize that everything in this world is just a לבוש, Levush,
a garment, for the אלוקות Elokus that is hidden within it. And
our job is to peel away those layers
and to find the אחדות Achdus of ה' Hashem in every single
thing. As we go through this week, let us try to keep
this in mind and to look past the external world and to
see the יד ה' Yad Hashem in everything we do. Wishing everyone
a שבת שלום. Shabbat Shalom. And the גמרא Gemara explains the difference
in their opinions. But when we look at our
סידור Siddur today, in ברכות השחר, Birkot HaShachar, we follow the opinion
of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, and we say שלא עשני גוי, Shelo
asani goy, שלא עשני עבד, Shelo asani eved, and שלא עשני
אשה. Shelo asani isha. The משנה Mishna then says: אלו דברים שאדם
אוכל פירותיהם בעולם הזה והקרן קיימת לו לעולם
הבא. Elu devarim she'adam ochel peiroteihem ba'olam hazeh vehakeren kayemet lo l'olam
haba. These are the things that a person enjoys the fruits of
in this world, while the principal remains
for him in the world to come. They are: כיבוד אב ואם,
Kibbud av va'eim, honoring father and mother; וגמילות
חסדים, ugemilut chasadim, acts of kindness; והבאת שלום בין אדם לחברו, vehav'at
shalom bein adam lachaveiro, and bringing peace between
a person and his fellow; ותלמוד תורה כנגד כולם, vetalmud torah keneged
kulam, but the study of Torah is equal to them all. The
תורה Torah says in the end of פרשת מקץ, Parshas Mikeitz, we
have ויהי vayehi and the בני יעקב Bnei Yaakov are coming
down to מצרים. Mitzrayim. Then they find by בנימין
Binyamin the גביע. gavia. And it says that יהודה Yehuda and his
brothers
came back to the house of יוסף. Yosef. והוא עודנו שם, vehu
odenu sham, he was still there. Then they
fell down on their faces to the floor. יוסף Yosef said to
them, מה המעשה הזה אשר עשיתם? mah hama'aseh hazeh asher asitem? What's
this act that you did? הלא ידעתם כי נחש ינחש איש אשר
כמוני? halo yedatem ki nachesh yenachesh ish asher kamoni? Don't you know
that a man
like me can guess? I have the powers
to know everything. יהודה Yehuda answered and said, מה
נאמר לאדוני? mah nomar ladoni? What can we say to my
master? מה נדבר ומה נצטדק? mah nedaber u'mah nitztadak? What can we
speak? How can we justify ourselves? האלוקים מצא
עוון עבדיך. ha'elokim matza avon avadecha. השם Hashem found the sin of
your servants. What does it mean? רש״י Rashi brings from the מדרש,
Midrash האלוקים מצא עוון עבדיך. ha'elokim matza avon avadecha. Not that we
took the גביע. gavia. We didn't take the cup. We didn't do
this sin. But השם Hashem is finding our old sins. There's
a lot of things that we did in our past, and this
is the time that השם Hashem is collecting the debt. What does
it mean in our personal life? A person sometimes goes
through a hard time, difficult times, hardships. And
he says, "I didn't do anything wrong! I'm
a good guy, why did this happen to
me?" Wait a second. What happened in your past? Everything is recorded.
There is a notebook. And even though sometimes
we do something wrong and we forget it,
but השם Hashem doesn't forget. And sometimes He brings
a difficult situation just to collect the debt. He didn't forget what
we did in the past. Wait, so there's no hope? Does that
mean whatever we did we have to pay
for it? The answer is: there is תשובה.
teshuva. If we do תשובה, teshuva, if we do
תשובה, teshuva, then the whole debt is erased. It says in the
גמרא, Gemara גדולה תשובה שמגעת עד כיסא הכבוד. gedolah teshuva shemaga'as ad
kisei hakavod. The power of תשובה teshuva is so high that it
goes to the throne of השם. Hashem. And through תשובה, teshuva, we
can
clean everything from the past. So, when things are difficult, instead of
saying, "Why me?" we should say, "Let's look into our actions." Let's
see what we can fix. Let's do תשובה.
teshuva. Because once the תשובה teshuva is done, then
the judgment is gone. The same way השם Hashem brought the brothers
of יוסף Yosef to this difficult situation, He wanted
them to reach that point of תשובה. teshuva. Once they said, האלוקים
מצא עוון עבדיך, ha'elokim matza avon avadecha, השם Hashem found our old
sins, they realized what they did was wrong and
they wanted to fix
it. And once the process of תשובה teshuva was complete, then the
salvation came. Then יוסף Yosef revealed himself to them, and it ended
with joy. So, the message is: always look into our actions and
know that everything can be fixed with תשובה.
teshuva. It gives them כח, Koach, it gives them
strength. We see by the רבי, Rebbe, the רבי's Rebbe name was
מנחם מענדל. Menachem Mendel. The גמרא Gemara in מסכת סנהדרין
Masechet Sanhedrin tells us that the name of משיח Moshiach is מנחם,
Menachem, and we are waiting for the גאולה. Geulah. And מנחם Menachem
also means to comfort. We need that נחמה, Nechama, we need that
comfort, and we should have
it speedily in our days with the coming of משיח, Moshiach, אמן.
Amen. Have you ever noticed how many donkeys
there are in the Bible? I mean, think of Abraham going to
the binding of
Isaac. Early in the morning, says the Torah, וישכם אברהם בבקר ויחבש
את חמרו, Vayashkem Avraham baboker vayachavosh et chamoro, Abraham rose early and
saddled his donkey. Think of Moses when he's going back to Egypt
to lead the Israelites to freedom. The Torah says, ויקח משה את
אשתו ואת בניו וירכיבם על החמור, Vayikach Moshe et ishto ve'et banav
vayarkivem al hachamor, Moses took his wife and children
and set them on the donkey. And think of the Messiah. The
prophet Zechariah says he will be עני ורכב
על חמור,
Ani verochev
al chamor,
a humble man riding on a donkey. Now, the מדרש Midrash says
a very strange thing. It says it was the same donkey. Abraham's
donkey was Moses's donkey was the Messiah's donkey. Now,
donkeys don't live for thousands of years. What did the rabbis mean?
They meant this. The word
for donkey in Hebrew is חמור. chamor. And the word for physical
matter is חומר.
chomer.
The
hero in Judaism is not the person who retreats from the world,
the person who lives in a monastery
or a hermitage. The hero is the person who
can saddle the חמור, chamor, who can take the physical world and
make it a vehicle
for a journey to God. That's what Abraham did. That's
what Moses did. And that's what the Messiah will eventually do for
all of us. He will show us how to take the חומר,
chomer, the physical world, and make it
a vehicle for the spirit. The provided audio contains only static noise
and no intelligible speech.
Therefore, a transcription cannot be produced. We're starting today in the eighth
פרק Perek of מסכת שבת. Masechet Shabbat. The משנה Mishnah says, המוציא
יין כדי מזיגת הכוס, Ha-motzi yayin kedei mezigat ha-kos, if someone carries
out wine in an amount enough to
mix a cup. We're talking about the laws of הוצאה Hotza'ah on
שבת. Shabbat. If you carry something
from a רשות היחיד, Reshut HaYachid, a private domain, to a רשות
הרבים,
Reshut
HaRabim,
a public domain, you are חייב, Chayav, liable. But there is a
certain
שיעור, Shiur, a minimum amount, that you have
to carry to be liable
for a קרבן חטאת. Korban Chatat. For wine, the שיעור Shiur is
enough to mix a cup of wine. The גמרא
Gemara
explains that in those days, wine was very strong, and they
would mix it with three parts of water.
So the amount of wine needed was one quarter of
a רביעית. Revi'it. We're going to talk about the contribution of the
women, which is often overlooked but was
absolutely essential to the creation of the משכן. Mishkan. If we look
at פרשת ויקהל, Parshat Vayakhel, we see
that it wasn't just the men who were involved. The פסוק pasuk
says, ויבואו
האנשים על הנשים, Vayavo'u ha'anashim al hanashim, and the מפרשים mefarshim explain
that the women actually came
first. They were the ones who were most eager to give, most
eager to contribute their jewelry and their talents
to this holy project. In fact, the נשים
צדקניות, nashim tzidkaniyot, the righteous women of that generation, had
a specific role in creating the יריעות, yeriyot, the curtains. The תורה
Torah tells us that they spun the goat hair while
it was still on the backs of the goats—חכמה יתירה, chochmah yetirah,
an extra measure of
wisdom and skill.
This teaches us that the משכן Mishkan wasn't just
a project of the leaders or the craftsmen like בצלאל Betzalel
and אהליאב. Oholiav. It was a project of the entire community, and
specifically,
the heart and the soul of the women brought
a unique level of קדושה kedushah and devotion that made the שכינה
Shechinah truly feel at home. This message is so important for us
today because it reminds us that every person,
regardless of their role or their gender, has a vital part to
play in
building a בית for השם Hashem in this world. It’s not about
how big the contribution is, but the devotion and the heart, the
נדיבות לב, nedivut lev, that we bring to it.
When we think about
the
concept of נדיבות לב, nedivut
lev, we
often think of it as just being generous. But in the context
of
the משכן, Mishkan,
it's something
much deeper. It's about a willingness to open oneself up and to
dedicate one's very essence to a higher purpose.
The כלי יקר Kli Yakar
notes that the word תרומה Terumah can be broken down into תרי
ומאה, trei u'me'ah, which refers to the hundred blessings
we say every day
and the two
tablets of
the ברית. Brit. This suggests that our physical contributions are
only meaningful when they are infused with our
spiritual practice and our commitment to
the מצוות. mitzvot. The physical structure
of the משכן Mishkan was temporary,
but the spirit of נדיבות לב nedivut lev is eternal. It’s what
allowed
the שכינה Shechinah to continue to dwell among us even after
the חורבן, churban, the destruction of
the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Today, we don't have a physical
משכן Mishkan made of gold and silver, but we
have our בתי כנסיות batei chenesiyot and our בתי מדרשות,
batei midrashot, and most importantly, we have our
own homes and our own hearts. By cultivating
that same נדיבות לב, nedivut lev, we can continue to build a
מקדש Mikdash in our own lives. Another fascinating aspect of the women's
contribution was
the מראות הצובאות, marot hatzove'ot, the mirrors of
the women who congregated. These
were the copper mirrors
that the women had used in מצרים Mitzrayim to
beautify themselves and to encourage their husbands during
the bitterness of slavery. When it came time to
build the כיור,
Kiyor,
the washstand, משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu was initially hesitant to use
these mirrors. He thought they were objects of
vanity, perhaps not suitable for
the קודש. Kodesh. But הקדוש ברוך הוא HaKadosh Baruch Hu said to
him, 'Accept them, for these are dearer to
Me than all
the other contributions.' These mirrors
represented the power of hope and
the ability to
find beauty and life even in
the darkest of times. By turning those mirrors into the כיור, Kiyor,
the women transformed physical beauty into spiritual purity. Every
time the כהנים Kohanim washed their hands and feet, they
were reminded of
the strength and the faith
of the women. This
reminds us that
nothing is inherently profane; everything in this world
can be elevated and used for a holy
purpose if we have the right intention, the right כוונה. kavanah. As
we reflect on these lessons, we see that
the משכן Mishkan is not just a piece of history. It's
a blueprint for spiritual living. It teaches us
about the importance of community,
the power of
generosity, the role of every individual, and
the ability to find holiness in
the mundane. Whether it's through
the way we treat our neighbors,
the way we perform our מצוות, mitzvot, or
the way we transform our physical environment, we are
all builders of a משכן. Mishkan. We are all
responsible for bringing more אור, or, more light, into
this world and for creating a space where
the שכינה Shechinah can truly dwell. May we all be
inspired by the example of
the בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael
in the desert and work together to build a world
that is a fitting home for
the Divine. Regarding הלל, if
the מנין minyan is in the house of
the אבל, avel, הלל is generally not said, or said
in private, so as not to be מצער
matzair
the נפטר. niftar. Every single thing we do has a
תיקון. tikkun. Every single thing we do is part
of a larger plan. And when we live
with that awareness, then our whole perspective on
life changes. We realize that we're not just
here by accident. We're here on a mission.
We are each a שליח shaliach of the רבונו של עולם Ribono
Shel Olam to bring light into this world, to make this world
a דירה בתחתונים, dirah betachtonim, a dwelling place for
the שכינה. Shechinah. Every single word of
the גמרא Gemara is precious. The גמרא Gemara says on דף
כא עמוד א,
Daf Kaf-Aleph
Amud Aleph,
the משנה Mishnah says, אלו מציאות שלו ואלו חייב להכריז. Elu metziot
shelo ve'elu chayav lehachriz. These are
the things which belong to him and these are
the things he is obligated to announce. אלו מציאות
שלו: Elu metziot shelo: פירות מפוזרים, Peirot mefuzarim, מעות מפוזרות, Ma'ot mefuzarot,
כריכות ברשות הרבים, Kerichot b'reshut harabbim, ועיגולי דבילה, Ve'igulei deveilah, ככרות של
נחתום, Kikarot shel nachtom, מחרוזות של דגים, Machrozot shel dagim, וחתיכות של
בשר, Vechatichot shel basar, וגזי צמר, Vegezei tzemer, הרי אלו שלו. Harei
elu shelo. Now the גמרא Gemara asks, why are these his? It's
because of יאוש. Ye'ush. But isn't it יאוש שלא
מדעת? Ye'ush shelo mada'at? The גמרא Gemara explains that because they are
scattered, the person knows right away and he has יאוש Ye'ush immediately.
This is how we distinguish between things that have a סימן Siman
and things that do not have a סימן.
Siman. The concept of יאוש שלא מדעת Ye'ush shelo mada'at is at
the heart of this סוגיא. As we learn in
ישיבה, Yeshiva, we must be careful with every single
word. The רן Ran and
the ריף Rif also discuss these rules of אבידה. Aveidah. The
משנה Mishna in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia is where we find all
the rules of returning a lost item, known as
השבת אבידה. Hashavat Aveidah. ארבעה ראשי שנים הם. Arba'ah rashei shanim hem.
באחד בניסן be-echad be-Nisan ראש השנה Rosh ha-Shanah למלכים ולרגלים. la-melachim ve-la-regalim.
באחד באלול be-echad be-Elul ראש השנה Rosh ha-Shanah למעשר בהמה. le-ma'asar behemah.
רבי אלעזר ורבי שמעון אומרים Rabbi Elazar ve-Rabbi Shimon omrim באחד בתשרי.
be-echad be-Tishrei. באחד בתשרי be-echad be-Tishrei ראש השנה Rosh ha-Shanah לשנים ולשמיטין
וליובלות, le-shanim u-le-shmitin u-le-yovelot, לנטיעה ולירקות. la-neti'ah ve-la-yerakot. באחד בשבט be-echad be-Shevat
ראש השנה Rosh ha-Shanah לאילן la-ilan כדברי בית שמאי. ke-divrei Beit Shammai.
בית הלל אומרים Beit Hillel omrim בחמישה עשר בו. ba-chamishah asar bo.
So let's dive deeper into this idea of
אמת. emet In the context of the Torah, when we say something
is true, what does that really mean? Is it just factual accuracy?
Actually, there's a fascinating connection made between the word אמת emet and
the letters that form it. You have אלף,
aleph,
the first letter of
the אלף בית. aleph bet. Then you have מם, mem, which is
the middle letter. And finally, you have תיו, tav, which is
the very last letter. This encompasses everything from
the beginning, middle, and end. It's
comprehensive. Now, contrast that with the word שקר, sheker, meaning falsehood. The
letters ש, shin, ק, kuf, and ר resh are all right
next to each other at the end of
the alphabet. Falsehood is crowded, narrow, and lacks
the structural stability of truth. Truth stands on a
firm foundation. We see this
in the גמרא Gemara where it discusses how
the letters of אמת emet each have two legs, making
them stable, while
the letters of שקר sheker only have one leg, making
them prone to falling over. This illustrates that
truth has legs to stand on, but a
lie does not. This concept is vital in
our daily lives, in how we conduct our
עסקים, asakim, our business dealings, and how we interact
with our חברים, chaverim, our friends. We must strive
to be אנשי אמת, anshei emet, people of truth, because
that reflects the essence of the בורא עולם, Borei Olam, the Creator
of the world. As we go through our day, let's
keep in mind that being truthful isn't just
about not telling a lie; it's about building
a life that is sustainable and upright, much
like the letters of the word אמת emet. themselves. Thank you for
joining us on
the עיון Iyun podcast. Until next time, stay committed to
the path of אמת. Good morning. We're going to look at
the first משנה Mishna in
the second פרק Perek of מסכת ברכות. Masechet Brachot. The משנה says
היה קורא בתורה והגיע זמן המקרא אם כיון
לבו יצא. Hayah korei batorah vehigiah zman hamikra, im kivein libo yatza.
What does it mean אם כיון לבו? im kivein libo? The
גמרא Gemara on דף ו עמוד א Daf Vav Amud Aleph discusses
whether מצוות צריכות כוונה. Mitzvot tzrichot kavanah. Some say that it
means he focused on the words, whereas others say he must have
the intent to
fulfill the מצוה. mitzvah. The רשבא Rashba explains that even according to
the view that מצוות צריכות כוונה, Mitzvot tzrichot kavanah, if one is
reading
the specific section of
the תורה Torah that constitutes the מצוה,
mitzvah,
the act of reading itself might demonstrate enough כוונה.
kavanah. This is a major יסוד yesod in understanding
how we approach our daily תפילה. tefillah. We often
find ourselves
saying the words without thinking, but
the הלכה halacha. requires us to at least have
the initial כוונה kavanah to fulfill our obligation. That if
the nations of
the world will come and say to ישראל, Yisrael, לסטים
אתם, Listim atem, you are robbers, you've conquered the land of
the seven nations, we'll answer them:
the whole world belongs to
the הקדוש ברוך הוא. Hakadosh Baruch Hu. He created it and He
gives it to whoever is right in His
eyes. By His will He gave it to
them and by His will He took it
from them and gave it to us. This is the very first
piece of
the תורה Torah that we learn as children. It's
the very foundation of our connection to ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael. אלוקי אברהם Elokei Avraham בעזרו,
be'ezro,
the God of אברהם Avraham is helping him, and when
he passes away,
the גמרא Gemara says we say about him אי ענו
אי חסיד, ei anav ei chassid, what a humble man, what a
pious man, he was a תלמיד talmid of אברהם אבינו. Avraham Avinu.
And the גמרא Gemara asks, how do we know that אברהם
אבינו Avraham Avinu himself had a קובע מקום? koveia makom?
And the גמרא Gemara says, because
the פסוק pasuk says, וישכם אברהם בבקר אל המקום אשר
עמד שם. Vayashkem Avraham baboker el hamakom asher amad sham. He went
back to
the place where he had stood. And
the גמרא Gemara says, אין עמידה אלא תפילה. ein amida ela tefillah.
Standing means תפילה. tefillah. So אברהם Avraham went back to
the same place that he had prayed
the day before. What about יצחק? Yitzchak? Did יצחק אבינו
Yitzchak Avinu also have a קובע מקום? koveia makom? The
פסוק pasuk says, ויצא יצחק לשוח בשדה. Vayetze Yitzchak lasuach basadeh. He
went out to
the field. And we know that שדה sadeh refers to
the same place, הר המוריה. Har Hamoriah. And יעקב אבינו. Yaakov Avinu.
The פסוק pasuk says, ויפגע במקום. Vayifga bamakom. He encountered
the place, which refers to
the same מקום makom of his fathers. We are coming now to
the climax of the ימים
נוראים, Yomim Noraim, the holy day of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. We
know that
the פייטן paytan says in ונתנה תוקף, Unesaneh Tokef, ותשובה ותפילה
וצדקה מעבירין את רוע הגזירה. u'teshuvah u'tefillah u'tzedakah ma'avirin et ro'ah hagezeirah.
We do our best with תשובה teshuvah and תפילה,
tefillah, but there is something very special about
צדקה. tzedakah. When we show רחמנות rachmanut to others, the רבונו של
עולם Ribono shel Olam shows רחמנות rachmanut to us. There is no
greater way to show that love for another
Jew than by helping בוני עולם. Bonei Olam. They are there for
the couples who are waiting, who are crying, who
are praying for a child of their own.
Your help allows them to build a בית
נאמן בישראל. bayis ne'eman b'Yisrael. Please, in these final moments before
the holy day, give with an open heart. May
this tremendous זכות zechut bring you and your family
a גמר חתימה טובה, gmar chasimah tovah, a year of health,
happiness, and נחת. nachas. Welcome back to
the weekly חסידות Chassidus on
the פרשה. Parshah. We are beginning ספר ויקרא,
Sefer
Vayikra,
the third book of
the תורה. Torah. The very first word of the ספר,
sefer,
the very first word of
the פרשה parshah is ויקרא. Vayikra. And there's a very famous
feature of this word in
the ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, which is that the final
letter, the letter א, aleph, is written smaller than
the other letters, what we call an א זעירא,
aleph zeira, a small א. aleph. And
the מדרש explains that this was at
the request of משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu himself. Because
the word ויקרא, Vayikra, with an א, aleph, means that השם
Hashem called out to משה. Moshe. It's
a term of endearment, of חיבה. chibah. It's
an invitation to a conversation. But משה Moshe in
his great ענווה, anavah, his humility, he didn't want
it to be written that way. He wanted
it to be written without the א, aleph, which would
make the word ויקר. Vayikar. And ויקר Vayikar means that השם Hashem
just happened to happen upon him, just like
by the wicked בלעם. Bilaam. It says ויקר אלקים אל בלעם,
Vayikar Elokim el Bilaam, that it was a
chance encounter, a מקרה. mikreh. So משה Moshe said I'm
not worthy of a special call of affection.
Let it just be written like a chance
encounter. And הקדוש ברוך הוא HaKadosh Baruch Hu didn't want that.
He insisted that the א aleph be there. So they compromised on
a small א. aleph. Now חסידות Chassidus explains that there's a very
deep lesson here for every single one of us. Because
the word ויקר Vayikar
without the א aleph means coldness, like
the word קר, kar, cold. It also means מקרה, mikreh, chance.
If we live a life of ויקר, Vayikar, we see
the world as just a series of random events,
a series of accidents, and we remain cold to
the presence of השם. Hashem. But when we add the א,
aleph,
the א aleph stands for אלופו של עולם, Alufo Shel Olam, the
Master of
the World. We take
the מקרה, mikreh, we take
the accidents of life, and we put
the א aleph into them. We recognize that even
the things that seem like a chance encounter, even
the things that seem like an accident, they are
really a ויקרא. Vayikra. They are really a personal
call from הקדוש ברוך הוא HaKadosh Baruch Hu to us. And
this is the beginning of
the whole עבודה avodah of קרבנות, korbanos, of sacrifices. The word
קרבן korban comes from
the word קרוב, karov, to come close. In order to
come close to השם, Hashem, we have to transform
the ויקר Vayikar into ויקרא. Vayikra. We have to take
the coldness and the randomness of
the world and find the א, aleph, find
the אלופו של עולם Alufo Shel Olam within it. And through that
we become close to הקדוש ברוך הוא. HaKadosh Baruch Hu. Have
a wonderful שבת. Shabbos. Okay tonight we're going to
be talking about
the מצווה mitzvah of תפילין. tefillin. I want to explore a
little bit deeper
the significance of this מצווה mitzvah beyond just
the physical act. We know that
the גמרא Gemara in מסכת ברכות Masechet Berachot says something very interesting.
It says מניין שהקדוש ברוך הוא מניח תפילין?
minayin she'Hakadosh Baruch Hu maniach tefillin? Where do
we know that
the Holy One Blessed Be He wears תפילין? tefillin? This
seems very strange. Hashem doesn't have a body.
What does it mean that He wears תפילין?
tefillin? The גמרא Gemara explains that in our תפילין
tefillin we have פסוקים pesukim that talk about the אחדות achdut of
Hashem. שמע ישראל ה' אלקינו ה' אחד. Shema Yisrael Hashem Elokeinu Hashem
Echad. But in
the תפילין tefillin of Hashem so to speak what's written
there? ומי כעמך ישראל גוי אחד בארץ. u'mi k'amcha Yisrael goy echad
ba'aretz. Who is like Your nation Israel, a
unique nation
on the earth? This teaches us a fundamental יסוד in
our relationship with
the רבונו של עולם. Ribono shel Olam. The relationship is reciprocal. Just
as we proclaim His oneness, He, so to
speak, proclaims our uniqueness. When a person puts
on תפילין, tefillin, it's not just a ritual. It's
a connection. It's a קשר. kesher. In fact, the word for the
knot of
the תפילין tefillin is a קשר. kesher. We are binding ourselves to
the בורא עולם. Borei Olam. And at
the same time, we're recognizing that He is bound to
us. There's a beautiful concept brought down in
חסידות. Chasidut. That the תפילין tefillin represent
the subjection of the heart and
the mind. The תפילין של יד tefillin shel yad is placed opposite
the heart to subjugate our desires and our emotions
to Hashem. The תפילין של ראש tefillin shel rosh is placed on
the head to subjugate our intellect and our thoughts.
By doing this, we align our entire being with
the divine will. It's
not just about the boxes and the straps. It's
about the כוונה, kavanah, the intention. When we say
the לשם יחוד L'shem Yichud before putting them on, we are
setting our focus. Every single morning we have
this opportunity to renew that bond, to remember
who we are and who our Creator is.
And as we wrap the straps around our arm we say וארשתיך
לי לעולם, v'erastich li l'olam, I will betroth you to Me forever.
It's
a marriage proposal, a daily renewal of the covenant between us and
Hashem. So next time you put on your תפילין, tefillin, think about
this. Think about
the incredible זכות zechut we have to wear
the same garment so to speak that
the רבונו של עולם Ribono shel Olam wears, to be connected in
such a deep and profound way. May we
all be זוכה zocheh to feel that connection every
day. The גמרא Gemara says that on
the יום טוב Yom Tov of שבועות Shavuot everyone agrees that we
need לכם lachem because on this day
the תורה Torah was given. But on every other יום
טוב Yom Tov it's a מחלוקת whether it has to
be חציו לה' וחציו לכם, chetzyo L'Hashem v'chetzyo lachem, half for Hashem
and half for you, or can you spend
it או כולו לה' או כולו לכם, o kulo L'Hashem o kulo
lachem, entirely for Hashem or entirely for you.
But on שבועות, Shavuot, everyone agrees you need לכם.
lachem. The reason is, as the רש"י Rashi says, because it's the
day
the תורה Torah was given. We have to show that
we are happy that
the תורה Torah was given to us. Therefore, we have
a סעודה. seudah. It's
the only יום טוב Yom Tov where there's no disagreement that
you need to have a physical enjoyment. Wait
a second. There is such a thing as
a גט get with a תנאי. tenai. Let's say I
gave a גט get on condition that you give
me two hundred זוז zuz and then she didn't give the two
hundred זוז, zuz, so
the גט get is not a גט. get. You're saying now
that let's say a guy is going to
die and he tells his wife, I'm giving
you a גט get on condition that I die.
Does he have to say if I die
from this sickness or just if I die?
If he says if I die from this
sickness and he dies from this sickness, the גט get is a
גט. get. If he says if I die and he dies from
this sickness, it's also a גט. get. But what if he says
if I die from this sickness and he gets better from the
sickness and then he dies from something else?
Then it's not a גט. get. This is what
we call a גט get שכיב מרע. shchiv meira. It is
a גט get given by a person who is
on his deathbed. Why does he do this?
He does this so she doesn't fall to
יבום. yibum. If they have no children, she would
have to do חליצה chalitzah or יבום yibum with the brother. To
save her from that, he gives her a גט get before he
dies. But it has to be done correctly. It has to be
מעכשיו, me'achshav, from now, if I die. Because a גט get after
death is nothing. You can't give a גט get to a dead
person or from a dead person. So the חלות, chalos, the taking
effect of
the גט, get, has to be while he's still alive.
That's why we use
the language of מעכשיו. me'achshav. We learned in מסכת גיטין
Masechet Gittin that when a person gives a
גט get to his wife, he has to do
it with a full heart. It cannot be
under duress. This is because the תורה Torah wants a person's actions
to be a reflection of their true רצון,
ratzon, their will. This idea of רצון ratzon is
very important
during the ימים נוראים. Yamim Noraim. We ask הקדוש ברוך הוא HaKadosh
Baruch Hu to accept our תפילות tefillos and to
see our deep רצון ratzon to be better. Even
if we have failed in our מעשים, ma'asim, our
actions, our inner רצון ratzon can still be pure.
This is what we mean when we say in the תפילה, tefillah,
אבינו מלכנו עשה למען שמך. Avinu Malkeinu aseh l'ma'an shemecha. We are
asking for mercy because we are his children. May we
all be זוכה zocha to a שנה טובה ומתוקה.
shana tova umesuka. The first thing it says
is, it says there, על פירות האילן הוא
אומר בורא פרי העץ. al peirot ha'ilan hu omer borei pri ha'eitz.
On fruit from the tree, one says, "He who creates the fruit
of
the tree." חוץ מן היין, chutz min hayayin, except for wine; שעל
היין הוא אומר בורא פרי הגפן, she'al hayayin hu omer borei pri
hagafen, because on wine, one says, "He who creates
the fruit of the vine." Now
the גמרא Gemara asks a question. Why is wine different?
If it comes from a tree, from a
vine, why do we change
the ברכה? beracha? The גמרא Gemara says because wine is special. Wine
has the ability to make a person happy. It's
חמרא סעד ומשמח, chamra sa'ad umesame'ach, wine sustains and makes one
happy. Therefore, חכמים Chachamim established a unique ברכה beracha for
it. Instead of בורא פרי העץ, Borei pri ha'eitz, we say
בורא פרי הגפן. Borei pri hagafen. This shows the importance of wine
in our מסורת. masoret. We use it for קידוש, Kiddush, for הבדלה,
Havdalah, and for various שמחות. simchot. It's not just another fruit juice.
It's
something that has a higher level of קדושה.
kedusha. And that's why we have to be
careful with how we treat it and how
we make the ברכה beracha on it. We also see this idea
in other areas of הלכה. For example, when it comes to bread,
we don't just say בורא פרי האדמה, Borei pri ha'adamah, even though
wheat grows from the ground. We say המוציא
לחם מן הארץ Hamotzi lechem min ha'aretz because bread is
the most important food. It's
the basis of a meal. Just like wine is
the most important drink, bread is
the most important food. And therefore, they both get
special ברכות. berachot. A ייד Yid cannot choose to not have
the תורה. Torah. This connection is an absolute necessity. It's
an ontological reality of who we are. The
מהר"ל Maharal explains that this is why the גמרא Gemara says, כפה
עליהם הר כגיגית. Kafah Aleihem Har Ke'gigit. A גיגית gigit is a
vat. It's
a circular vessel that surrounds everything inside. When
the mountain was held over them like a גיגית, gigit, it meant
they were encompassed by
the reality of the תורה. Torah. Now,
the גמרא in מסכת שבת Masechet Shabbat continues that this creates
a מודעא רבה לאורייתא, moda'ah raba l'Oraita, a great disclaimer or protest
against
the תורה. Torah. Since we were forced, we have an
excuse if we don't keep it. But then
the גמרא says, אמר רבא אף על פי כן
הדור קבלוה בימי אחשורוש, Amar Rava af al pi chen hadar kibluha
bimei Achashverosh, even so, they re-accepted it in
the days of אחשורוש. Achashverosh. As
the פסוק pasuk says in מגילת אסתר, Megillat Esther, קימו וקבלו היהודים,
Kiyemu v'kiblu haYehudim, they established and they accepted.
They established what they had already accepted at
הר סיני. Har Sinai. Why was פורים
Purim the
time for this? At הר סיני,
Har
Sinai,
the revelation was so powerful,
the גילוי שכינה gilluy Shechinah was so overwhelming, that they didn't
really have a choice. When you see
the King in all His glory, you can't say
no. That's why it's called כפייה, kefiyah, coercion. But in
the times of אסתר Esther and מרדכי, Mordechai, השם Hashem was hidden.
It was הסתר פנים. hester panim. There were no split
seas, no voices from
the fire. It was a world of nature and
politics. And yet,
the כלל ישראל stood strong. They chose to be loyal to
the תורה Torah even when
the light was not visible. That voluntary acceptance out
of love, out of מסירות נפש, mesirus nefesh, that completed
the process. That's why
the קבלה kabbalah of פורים Purim is in a sense even greater
than
the מעמד הר סיני. Ma'amad Har Sinai. It
turned the 'must' into a 'want'. It transformed
the relationship from one of external pressure to one
of internal desire. The משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah over here
explains in סעיף קטן יג: Seif Katan Yud-Gimel: ולא לאמן, velo le'Amen,
that
the reason why we don't stop is because שמונה
עשרה Shemoneh Esrei is unlike the rest
of the prayer. In ברכות קריאת שמע, Birkhot Kiriath Shema, you're allowed
to interrupt for certain things. In שמונה עשרה,
Shemoneh Esrei, you are standing before
the king. You are standing before הקדוש ברוך הוא,
HaKadosh Baruch Hu, and therefore we are much
more stringent. However,
the משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah does point out that if a
person already finished his prayer, meaning he said
the second יהיו לרצון, Yehyu leratzon, even if he didn't take
the steps back yet, he would be allowed to answer to
the main parts of the קדיש Kaddish and
the קדושה. Kedusha. But he still wouldn't answer ברוך הוא
וברוך שמו Baruch Hu u'varuch Shemo even at that point. Now we
move on to סעיף ה. Seif Hei. The מחבר Mechaber writes:
נשים ועבדים פטורים מקריאת שמע, Nashim va'avadim peturim mikiriath shema, women and
slaves are exempt from the recital of קריאת שמע, Kiriath Shema, ומתפילין,
u'mitfillin, and from תפילין, Tefillin, מפני שהוא מצות עשה
שהזמן גרמא, mipnei shehu mitzvath aseh she'hazman gerama, because it is a
positive commandment that is time-bound. וחייבין בתפילה, vechayavin bitfillah, however
they are obligated in תפילה, Tefillah, משום דרחמי נינהו,
mishum derachamei ninhu, because prayer is a request
for mercy. The משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah in סעיף קטן
טו Seif Katan Tet-Vav explains that even though according to the strict
law
of the תורה Torah they could say any short prayer,
the חכמים Chachamim obligated them in
the formal prayer. Therefore, they should be careful to
pray both שחרית Shacharit and מנחה. Mincha. But for מעריב,
Maariv, they are exempt, as it was originally
an optional prayer. We are
continuing our discussion
of the month of טבת. Tevet. The month
of טבת Tevet corresponds to
the element of עפר, afar, earth. Earth represents
the physical world, the material reality
that we inhabit. In
the month of טבת,
Tevet,
the focus is on elevating
the physical world, on finding the holiness within the mundane.
This is connected
to the sense of רוגז,
rogez,
which is often translated
as anger, but
in this context, it refers
to a type of
agitation or movement. It's
the movement of the soul within
the body, trying to express itself through
the physical. The letter associated
with this month is
the letter עין. ayin. The word
עין ayin means eye. This
teaches us that our
task in טבת Tevet is
to change our perspective,
to develop a good
eye, an עין טובה.
ayin
tova.
When we look at
the world with an עין טובה, ayin tova, we
are able to see
the potential for goodness in everyone
and everything. Even in
the midst of the cold and
the dark, we can
find points of light. The
work of טבת Tevet is
the work of בירור, birur, of
clarification. We sift through
the material world to find
the sparks of holiness,
the ניצוצות, nitsotsot, that are
hidden there. This process
of בירור birur is what
allows us to
transform the darkness of טבת Tevet into a
source of light.
As we move through this month, let us focus
on our vision,
on how we see
ourselves and how we see
others. By cultivating an
עין טובה, ayin tova, we can
bring more light into
the world and hasten the גאולה,
geulah, the final redemption.